<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Daring Fireball</title>
    <subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main"/>
    <id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>
    <updated>2023-04-22T17:43:32Z</updated>
    <rights>Copyright © 2023, John Gruber</rights>
    <entry>
        <title>DF Sponsorship Openings</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uro"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/22/df-sponsorship-openings"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39876</id>
        <published>2023-04-22T17:43:32Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-22T17:43:32Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/22/kolide">Speaking of</a> weekly sponsorships,
                there’s only one opening left before the end of June: next week.</p>

            <p>Weekly sponsorships have been the top source of revenue for Daring Fireball ever since I started selling
                them <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">back in 2007</a>. They’ve succeeded, I
                think, because they make everyone happy. There’s only one sponsor per week and the sponsors are always
                relevant to at least some sizable portion of the DF audience, so you, the reader, are never annoyed and
                hopefully often intrigued by them. And, from the sponsors’ perspective, they work. My favorite thing
                about them is how many sponsors <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">return for
                    subsequent weeks</a> after seeing the results.</p>

            <p>If you’ve got a product or service you think would be of interest to DF’s audience of people obsessed
                with high quality and good design, <a
                        href="mailto:sponsors@daringfireball.net?subject=Feed%20Sponsorship">get in touch</a>. If this
                quarter is a sign, the summer months will start filling up soon. And as I mentioned above, if you’ve got
                something to promote right now, next week is the opening left this quarter.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘DF Sponsorship Openings’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/22/df-sponsorship-openings">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Kolide</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://l.kolide.co/3JWbXEv"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urn"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/22/kolide"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39875</id>
        <published>2023-04-22T17:37:12Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-22T17:37:13Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>My thanks to Kolide for their continuing sponsorship support here at DF — they co-sponsored <a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2023/03/31/ep-371">the latest episode of The Talk
                Show</a> that dropped last night, and they sponsored this entire week here at the website. They’re a
                great company with a great product.</p>

            <p>Here’s an uncomfortable fact: at most companies, employees can download sensitive company data onto any
                device, keep it there forever, and never even know that they’re doing something wrong. Kolide’s new
                report, <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3I7025A">The State of Sensitive Data</a>, addresses this issue
                head-on.</p>

            <p>Kolide offers a more nuanced approach than MDM solutions to setting and enforcing sensitive data
                policies. Their premise is simple: if an employee’s device is out of compliance, it can’t access your
                apps. Kolide lets admins run queries to detect sensitive data, flag devices that have violated policies,
                and enforce OS and browser updates so vulnerable devices aren’t accessing data.</p>

            <p>To learn more and see Kolide in action, <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3XlSqAq">visit kolide.com</a>.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Kolide’" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/22/kolide">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Talk Show: ‘$8 Billion in Late Fees’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2023/04/21/ep-372"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urm"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/21/the-talk-show-372"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39874</id>
        <published>2023-04-22T02:59:52Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-22T02:59:53Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Rene Ritchie returns to the show to discuss generative AI (and what Apple might soon do with it), iPhone
                passcodes and iCloud device security, HBO Max turning into just plain Max, and Make Something
                Wonderful  —  one more thing from Steve Jobs.</p>

            <p>Brought to you by:</p>

            <ul>
                <li><a href="squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Make your next move. Use code
                    <strong>talkshow</strong> for 10% off your first order.
                </li>
                <li><a href="http://kolide.com/thetalkshow">Kolide</a>: Cross-platform endpoint security solution for
                    teams that value privacy and transparency.
                </li>
            </ul>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘$8 Billion in Late Fees’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/21/the-talk-show-372">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/if_you_come_at_the_king"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/url"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023://1.39873</id>
        <published>2023-04-22T00:57:00Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-22T02:20:22Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <summary type="text">Anything that attempts to establish a post-phone beachhead has to do the things we love to
            do with our phones, or entertain us in new ways that make us forget about them. I don’t see how a laser
            projector on a chest badge does that.
        </summary>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Raymond Wong, reporting for Inverse, “<a
                    href="https://www.inverse.com/tech/humane-ai-wearable-camera-sensor-projector-video-demo">Watch
                Humane’s Wearable AI Projector in Action</a>”:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Humane, the top-secret tech startup founded by <a
                        href="https://www.inverse.com/input/tech/the-ipads-original-software-designer-and-program-lead-look-back-on-the-devices-first-10-years">ex-Apple
                    vets
                    Imran Chaudhri and Bethany Bongiorno</a>, just showed off the
                    first demo for its projector-based wearable at a TED talk.
                    <a href="https://www.axios.com/2023/04/21/humane-ai-powered-wearable">Axios’s Ina Fried broke the
                        news</a>, and Inverse has seen a
                    recording of the full TED talk given by Chaudhri.</p>

                <p>Journalist Zarif Ali, who had <a href="https://twitter.com/ZarifAli9/status/1649230439322664968">tweeted
                    out an image</a> of
                    Humane’s wearable projecting a phone call function onto Chaudhri’s
                    palm, says the full TED talk video is not slated to become
                    available until April 22.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>So the full video should be out tomorrow, but in the meantime, Wong has pulled a bunch of clips. There’s
                some cool technology being shown, including on-the-fly translation from English to French using an
                AI-trained version of Chaudhri’s own voice, but what I fundamentally don’t get about Humane is their
                anti-phone slant. Chaudhri emphasizes that you don’t need a phone to use the unnamed Humane device, but
                if the device can receive and place phone calls, and has a network connection, must not their device
                itself be ... a phone? Just a phone in a different form factor.</p>

            <p>Back in February when LeBron James broke the all-time NBA scoring title, <a
                    href="https://twitter.com/imranchaudhri/status/1624041258778763265">Chaudhri retweeted someone</a>
                comparing a photo of James’s record-breaking shot (with a seeming majority of the fans in the background
                holding their phones to capture the moment — <a
                        href="https://twitter.com/imranchaudhri/status/1624041258778763265">almost all of them
                    iPhones</a>, natch) with Michael Jordan’s iconic 1998 championship-winning shot against the Utah
                Jazz (with, of course, not a single fan with a phone in hand).<sup id="fnr1-2023-04-21"><a
                        href="#fn1-2023-04-21">1</a></sup> Chaudhri’s comment on the comparison: “we all deserve
                better.”</p>

            <p>The thought being, I surmise, that Chaudhri thinks something is wrong that so many of us turn to our
                phones to photograph or film major moments in our lives, rather than just enjoying them through our own
                senses. I get it to some degree. If I’d been at that Lakers game, my phone would’ve been in my pocket at
                that moment, not just to absorb the actual game experience, but because I know that no photo I could
                take could possibly be as as good as those being taken by courtside professional sports photographers.
                But those thousands of fans who did have their phones out for that moment weren’t thinking “<em>This
                    sucks, I wish I didn’t have to stare at my phone to capture this.</em>” They were thinking “<em>This
                    is awesome and I’m glad I can capture this.</em>”</p>

            <p>People take their own photos at major events not because they think those will be great photos, but
                because they’re proof that they were there. Selfies are the new autographs, and a shaky iPhone photo
                from the perspective of your own seat at the event is the new certificate of attendance.</p>

            <p>We still don’t know much about Humane’s device, as Wong’s colleague at Inverse <a
                    href="https://www.inverse.com/tech/humane-wearable-ai-projector-apps-price">Ian Carlos Campbell
                notes in this follow-up piece</a>. But everything we do know seems positioned around the notion of
                relieving us of the burden of being tethered to our iPhones all day every day. The fundamental flaw in
                Humane’s entire premise, as I see it, is that people don’t feel burdened by their phones. People <em>love</em>
                them — especially iPhone owners. And those who are ambivalent or even downright antipathetic toward
                their phones surely aren’t the sort of people who are interested in a newfangled laser-projecting
                AI-driven chest-badge computer.</p>

            <p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/10/25/season-of-the-witch">I wrote about this all the way
                back in 2010</a>, in the era of the iPhone 4, when Microsoft debuted a high-budget ad campaign for their
                answer to the iPhone, Windows Phone 7. The ads were very entertaining — <a
                        href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lg1gbVGk19k">particularly this one</a> — but the whole
                premise was fundamentally flawed. Microsoft’s message was that if you switched to Windows Phone you
                wouldn’t need to stare at your phone all the time. The problem is that people stare at their phones all
                the time not because they have to but <em>because they want to</em>.</p>

            <p>“<em>Finally, you can replace this thing that you despise</em>” is a powerful marketing message. “<em>Finally,
                you can replace this thing that you love</em>” is not.</p>

            <p>So far, it feels like Humane’s entire premise is founded on that same mistake: building a new device
                intended to replace our phones, without that new device being able to do any of the dozens of things we
                <em>love</em> to do on our phones that require a display. Apple Watch and AirPods thrive because they’re
                satellites to our iPhones, not ostensible replacements. Our iPhones aren’t a burden — they’re a
                pleasure. I’m not arguing there are no downsides to our collective mass addiction to our phones. There’s
                undeniably a nostalgic appeal to many aspects of the pre-iPhone age. But the notion of even a single
                trip to the grocery store without a phone to provide (unlimited!) material to read or watch while I wait
                at the checkout line seems like veritable torture to me now. Anything that attempts to establish a
                post-phone beachhead has to do the things we love to do with our phones, or entertain us in new ways
                that make us forget about them. I don’t see how a laser projector on a chest badge does that.</p>

            <div class="footnotes">
                <hr/>
                <ol>
                    <li id="fn1-2023-04-21">
                        <p>Not only are there no fans with cell phones in hand in the Jordan photo, there are none with
                            <em>any</em> sort of camera in hand. Cell phone cameras were uncommon in 1998, but regular
                            cameras were not. But before the iPhone age, when such policies became untenable, events
                            like concerts and indoor sporting events banned cameras. Same thing with casinos. And even
                            if the rules didn’t prohibit cameras, people just didn’t have the habit of taking their own
                            photographs. Today we don’t just take photos with our phones instead of with standalone
                            cameras — we take thousands of photos every year that we never would have taken in the first
                            place, because we wouldn’t have had a camera with us. The best camera really is the one you
                            have with you.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2023-04-21" class="footnoteBackLink"
                                                   title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </div>


            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>★ If You Come at the King</title></entry>
    <entry>
        <title>BuzzFeed News Is Shutting Down</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.semafor.com/article/04/20/2023/the-end-of-the-buzzfeed-era-in-news"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urk"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/buzzfeed-news-shutting-down"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39872</id>
        <published>2023-04-21T03:38:19Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-22T03:18:38Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Ben Smith, writing at Semafor:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>My old boss and partner Jonah Peretti announced today that he’s
                    shutting down BuzzFeed News, which we built together starting
                    in 2012.</p>

                <p>He wrote to staff that he’d been ​​”slow to accept that the big
                    platforms wouldn’t provide the distribution or financial support
                    required to support premium-free journalism purpose-built for
                    social media.” And he wrote that he could have managed the many
                    business challenges that BuzzFeed has faced better.</p>

                <p>The news makes me heartsick.</p>

                <p>Peretti hired me in 2012 to build a news organization for the
                    exploding social web. For a few years, we felt the wind of
                    Facebook, Twitter, and Pinterest at our backs, and we did
                    journalism that treated those sites as the front page of the new
                    internet. At first, we celebrated and immersed ourselves in an
                    optimistic web culture that imagined a reader who cared about
                    which Disney princess she was, and also the <a
                            href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/alexcampbell/this-battered-woman-wants-to-get-out-of-prison">worst</a>
                    of how
                    the American justice system treated abused women, who wanted to
                    argue about the color of <a
                            href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/catesish/help-am-i-going-insane-its-definitely-blue?utm_term=.wnrMEoO6y#.agDJKQPRB">the
                        dress</a> and also understand the
                    <a href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/virginiahughes/science-of-the-dress">science</a>
                    behind it. That was back when all of it mixed up
                    in your Facebook feed, and it felt novel.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>BuzzFeed News did great work and employed some terrific reporters, but they <em>never</em> had a plan to
                turn a profit that made any more sense than that of <a
                        href="https://observer.com/2016/01/the-cautionary-tale-of-south-parks-underpants-gnomes/">the
                    underwear-collecting gnomes</a> on <em>South Park</em>.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘BuzzFeed News Is Shutting Down’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/buzzfeed-news-shutting-down">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Humane Previews AI-Powered Wearable at TED</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.axios.com/2023/04/21/humane-ai-powered-wearable"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urj"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/humane-ted-demo"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39871</id>
        <published>2023-04-21T02:28:57Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-21T19:32:56Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Ina Fried, reporting for Axios:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Ex-Apple employee Imran Chaudhri gave TED attendees on Thursday an
                    early glimpse of the AI-powered wearable that his startup, Humane,
                    has been developing. [...]</p>

                <p>The screenless device, which does not require a nearby cell phone
                    to work, uses a combination of voice and gestures for input and
                    can display information by projecting it onto nearby objects.</p>

                <p>Details: In his TED talk, Chaudhri showed the wearable, which sat
                    in his jacket pocket, translating his own voice into French.</p>

                <ul>
                    <li><p>He also answered a phone call from his wife with the call
                        information appearing as a green image projected onto his hand.</p></li>
                    <li><p>“This is good AI in action,” he said, promising more details
                        would be released in the coming months.</p></li>
                </ul>
            </blockquote>

            <p>The device — which seemingly doesn’t yet have an announced name? — looks about 2 inches wide and 1 inch
                high, and is worn on your chest like a Star Trek communicator badge. <a
                        href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/humane-ted-bethany-is-calling.jpeg">Here’s an
                    image of the phone call information projected onto Chaudhri’s hand</a>. Hope the whole demo is
                released on video soon.</p>

            <p><strong>Update:</strong> Actually, now that I look at the video clips that are available, I think the
                device is quite a bit bigger, and Chaudhri has it peaking out of a pocket on his jacket? Unclear.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Humane Previews AI-Powered Wearable at TED’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/humane-ted-demo">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>‘Arcade Game Typography’ by Toshi Omagari</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://readonlymemory.vg/shop/book/arcade-game-typography/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uri"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/arcade-game-typography"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39870</id>
        <published>2023-04-21T01:46:45Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-21T01:46:46Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Read-Only Memory, video game book publishers <a href="https://readonlymemory.vg">extraordinaire</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>The first book of its kind — a definitive and beautifully
                    designed survey of ’70s, ’80s and early ’90s arcade game pixel
                    typography. Exhaustively researched by author Toshi Omagari (a
                    celebrated typeface designer at Monotype UK) <em>Arcade Game
                        Typography</em> gathers together 250 pixel typefaces, all carefully
                    chosen, extracted, redrawn and categorised by style, and each with
                    an accompanying commentary by Omagari. The title also features 4
                    illustrated essays on videogame typography theory and practice,
                    documenting the unique advantages and challenges presented to
                    designers of these bold, playful and often quirky alphabets.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>I bought and devoured this book back in October 2019, but somehow never recommended it here on Daring
                Fireball. I should be arrested for dereliction of duty. But I was reminded of it today by <a
                        href="https://mastodon.social/@antonyjohnston/110232389169824182">this toot from Antony
                    Johnston</a>.</p>

            <p>A book about classic arcade game fonts is <em>so</em> obviously up my alley that I’d probably enjoy a bad
                book about them. But <em>Arcade Game Typography</em> is an exquisitely good book: deeply researched,
                beautifully illustrated with copious screenshots and close-up pixel-by-pixel details, and engagingly
                written by Omagari. I’m linking here to the limited edition hardcover, which costs $46, but <a
                        href="https://www.amazon.com/Arcade-Game-Typography-Pixel-Type/dp/0500021740/?tag=df-amzn-20">there’s
                    also a high-quality paperback edition for $28</a>. (Buy through that Amazon link and you’ll make me
                rich with a cut of the dough.) If you <em>don’t</em> want this book you’re either too young or you’re
                not hooked up right.</p>

            <p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C5NiAoT3xsY">Estelle Caswell
                interviewed Omagari in 2020 in a video for Vox</a>, focusing specifically on the 8x8 pixel Quiz Show
                font, a.k.a. <em>the</em> arcade font.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘‘Arcade Game Typography’ by Toshi Omagari’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/arcade-game-typography">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Oakland A’s Are Moving to Las Vegas</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/sports/athletics/major-league-deal-as-to-purchase-land-near-strip-for-new-ballpark-2764701/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urh"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/athletics-to-vegas"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39869</id>
        <published>2023-04-21T00:58:56Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-21T00:58:56Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Mick Akers, reporting for The Las Vegas Review-Journal:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>The Oakland Athletics have zeroed in on Southern Nevada, signing a
                    binding purchase agreement for land just west of the Strip where a
                    major-league ballpark could be constructed. The agreement is for
                    49 acres at Dean Martin Drive and Tropicana Avenue, owned by Red
                    Rock Resorts, parent company of Station Casinos.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>That’s close to T-Mobile Arena (home of the NHL Golden Knights), behind the New York New York casino
                complex.</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>“For a while we were on parallel paths (with Oakland), but we have
                    turned our attention to Las Vegas to get a deal here for the A’s
                    and find a long-term home,” A’s President Dave Kaval told the
                    Review-Journal on Wednesday. “Oakland has been a great home for us
                    for over 50 years, but we really need this 20-year saga completed
                    and we feel there’s a path here in Southern Nevada to do that.”</p>

                <p>With the announcement of the purchase agreement, MLB Commissioner
                    Rob Manfred concurs with Kaval and hopes the A’s shifting their
                    efforts solely to Southern Nevada will lead to the end of the
                    team’s <a
                            href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/sports/athletics/the-as-are-bad-would-a-move-to-vegas-help-2594529/">yearslong
                        quest to leave crumbling Oakland
                        Coliseum.</a></p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Recent embarrassments for the A’s in Oakland include a game against the Cleveland Guardians <a
                    href="https://whitecleatbeat.com/posts/the-season-just-started-and-the-oakland-a-s-attendance-is-already-embarrassing-01gxca55xk93">that
                drew just 3,000 fans</a>, and <a
                    href="https://www.sfgate.com/athletics/article/oakland-as-stink-worse-than-possum-poop-17905039.php">a
                possum that lives within the walls of the visiting press boxes</a>, which stunk them up so badly that
                the Mets’ broadcast team had to move to another box.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘The Oakland A’s Are Moving to Las Vegas’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/20/athletics-to-vegas">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/ios_adware"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/urg"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023://1.39868</id>
        <published>2023-04-20T14:41:43Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-20T14:41:44Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <summary type="text">Promotions for services I might want? Maybe, but Apple should be extremely conservative
            about presenting them — especially in push notifications. Promotions for services I already pay for? That
            shouldn’t happen.
        </summary>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p><a href="https://stevestreza.com/2020/02/17/ios-adware/">Steve Streza, all the way back in February
                2020</a> (innocent times, that month):</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Over the years, Apple has built up a portfolio of services and
                    add-ons that you pay for. Starting with AppleCare extended
                    warranties and iCloud data subscriptions, they expanded to Apple
                    Music a few years ago, only to dramatically ramp up their
                    offerings last year with TV+, News+, Arcade, and Card. Their
                    services business, taken as a whole, is quickly becoming massive;
                    Apple reported <a
                            href="https://www.macrumors.com/2020/01/28/apple-services-revenue-12-7-billion-q1-2020/">$12.7
                        billion in Q1 2020</a> alone, nearly a
                    sixth of its already gigantic quarterly revenue. [...]</p>

                <p>If you don’t subscribe to these services, you’ll be forced to look
                    at these ads constantly, either in the apps you use or the push
                    notifications they have turned on by default. The pervasiveness of
                    ads in iOS is a topic largely unexplored, perhaps due to these
                    services having a lot of adoption among the early adopter crowd
                    that tends to discuss Apple and their design. This isn’t a value
                    call on the services themselves, but a look at how aggressively
                    Apple pushes you to pay for them, and how that
                    <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Growth_hacking">growth-hack</a>-style design comes at the
                    expense of the user
                    experience. In this post, I’ll break down all of the places in iOS
                    that I’ve found that have Apple-manufactured ads. You can
                    replicate these results yourself by doing a factory reset of an
                    iPhone (backup first!), installing iOS 13, and signing up for a
                    new iCloud account.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Streza’s post emphasizes the new-user experience, and he’s right that longtime users (like you, dear
                reader, probably) don’t see a lot of this. But I do, because when reviewing new devices or new OS
                releases, I’ll sometimes set up as new (and use a spare Apple ID dedicated to testing) to see the
                factory-fresh Cupertino default experience. Is it too much advertising? I don’t know — but it’s a lot.
                One thing that’s clear is that Apple sees Music and TV as Apple-service properties. Yes, you can use
                them for listening to your own music and watching your own video files, but first and foremost these are
                client apps to Apple’s Music and TV+ services. These are not the iTunes and Video apps of yore.</p>

            <p>But what got me thinking about this issue this week is the dumbest adware in iOS I’ve seen. For the last
                several weeks, I’ve noticed <a
                        href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/ios-settings-arcade-ad.png">an ad in Settings on
                    my iPhone</a>, in the iCloud section at the very top of the first screen: “Apple Arcade Free for 3
                Months”. The reason this is dumb is that I pay for a family account for Apple One, <em>so we already
                    have Apple Arcade</em>. But here’s Apple badgering me to sign up for a 3-month free trial that I
                don’t need.</p>

            <p>If I tap into that ad’s section in Settings it explains why they’re offering it: “Services Included With
                Purchase”. I’m not even sure what device I bought that earned me this offer, but it shouldn’t matter.
                Why are they showing me something I already pay for?</p>

            <p>To be clear, I was able to make this ad go away by tapping “Not Now” on the offer screen in Settings. (I
                waited for weeks before doing so to see if it would go away on its own.) And I’m not blankly opposed to
                using this top-of-the-first-screen space in Settings to show offers for Apple’s services or AppleCare
                warranty coverage. But they ought to be presented conservatively, and with surgical precision. Apple is
                doing users a favor if they’re reminding them of offers — like three free months of Apple Arcade — that
                they’ve already qualified for with a hardware purchase. But it’s annoying and confusing that it’s the
                very app where I manage my Apple One subscription that’s suggesting I sign up for a service included in
                Apple One.</p>

            <p>We — including Apple itself and Tim Cook personally — decry the invasiveness of the surveillance
                advertising complex, by which they develop profiles of us so accurate that the ads they deliver are so
                on-point to our recent interests that millions of people falsely believe their devices are somehow
                surreptitiously listening to their real-world conversations. This stupid Apple Arcade prompt in Settings
                is the opposite: I’m being shown it because Apple knows I recently bought a new device from them, but
                somehow doesn’t know that I already pay them for a subscription that includes Arcade. How can they be so
                contextually unaware?</p>

            <p>Promotions for services I might want? Maybe, but Apple should be extremely conservative about presenting
                them — especially in push notifications. Promotions for services I already pay for? That shouldn’t
                happen.</p>


            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>★ Adware for Apple Services in iOS</title></entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Warren Buffett on Apple</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/04/12/warren-buffett-apple-iphone-loyalty/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urf"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/buffett-apple"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39867</id>
        <published>2023-04-20T00:22:45Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-20T00:22:46Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Warren Buffett, <a href="https://twitter.com/SquawkCNBC/status/1646136625355710464">asked on CNBC</a>
                about Berkshire Hathaway’s largest holding, Apple (<a
                        href="https://appleinsider.com/articles/23/02/15/berkshire-hathaway-now-owns-58-of-public-apple-stock">they
                    own nearly 6 percent of Apple’s stock</a>)</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>“If you’re an Apple user and somebody offers you $10,000, but the
                    only proviso is they’ll take away your iPhone and you’ll never be
                    able to buy another, you’re not going to take it. If they tell you
                    if you buy another Ford car — they’ll give you $10,000 not to do
                    that — you’ll take the $10,000 and you’ll buy a Chevy instead.”</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Buffett, famously, isn’t technically minded. But I think that helps him understand Apple’s value. He’s
                right: Apple’s moat is customer loyalty, and that loyalty is earned through user experiences that other
                companies <em>can’t</em> match.</p>

            <p>Using Ford and Chevy as his counterexamples is serendipitous, <a
                    href="https://twitter.com/carnage4life/status/1647997065589592064">as Dare Obasanjo quipped</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Someone should print this tweet out, frame it and give it to the
                    CEO of GM in commemoration of their decision to stop supporting
                    CarPlay in their vehicles.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>It’s true. The <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2023/04/general-motors-hates-your-iphone/">anger over
                GM’s decision to drop CarPlay</a> and Android Auto support in its EVs is really only anger about
                dropping CarPlay.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Warren Buffett on Apple’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/buffett-apple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>WhatsApp, Signal, and Other Secure Messaging Platforms Write Open Letter to the UK Government Defending
            End-to-End Encryption</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.whatsapp.com/an-open-letter"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ure"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/whatsapp-signal-uk-open-letter"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39866</id>
        <published>2023-04-19T23:55:56Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-21T02:53:06Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>From an open letter signed by the leaders of WhatsApp, Signal, Viber, and a few other secure
                services:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Proponents say that they appreciate the importance of encryption
                    and privacy while also claiming that it’s possible to surveil
                    everyone’s messages without undermining end-to-end encryption. The
                    truth is that this is not possible.</p>

                <p>We aren’t the only ones who share concerns about the UK Bill. The
                    United Nations has warned that the UK Government’s efforts to
                    impose backdoor requirements constitute “a paradigm shift that
                    raises a host of serious problems with potentially dire
                    consequences”. Even the UK Government itself has acknowledged the
                    privacy risks that the text of the Bill poses, but has said its
                    “intention” isn’t for the Bill to be interpreted this way.</p>

                <p>Global providers of end-to-end encrypted products and services
                    cannot weaken the security of their products and services to suit
                    individual governments. There cannot be a “British internet,” or a
                    version of end-to-end encryption that is specific to the UK.</p>

                <p>The UK Government must urgently rethink the Bill, revising it to
                    encourage companies to offer more privacy and security to its
                    residents, not less. Weakening encryption, undermining privacy,
                    and introducing the mass surveillance of people’s private
                    communications is not the way forward.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>I’m glad to see these companies defending end-to-end encryption, but this letter dances around the
                repercussions of this proposed legislation in the U.K. What they mean in the third paragraph quoted
                above is that if the legislation passes, people in the U.K. won’t be able to use WhatsApp or Signal or
                any other end-to-end encrypted service. Apple isn’t a signatory of the letter, but I think iMessage
                would be banned too.</p>

            <p>Some reports are portraying this as though these services would begrudgingly comply if the law passes,
                but they <em>can’t</em>. End-to-end encryption is inherent to the protocols. If end-to-end encrypted
                messaging is banned in the U.K., it won’t mean that WhatsApp, Signal, et al will somehow switch to
                insecure protocols in order to comply — it will mean that people in the U.K. can’t use these apps.</p>

            <p>It’s tough, messaging-wise, because coming right out and saying that <em>sounds</em> like these companies
                <em>won’t</em> comply, by choice. Laypeople seemingly can’t be made to understand that a “good-guys-only
                back door” is cryptographically impossible. But that’s the truth. <a
                        href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1311229/whatsapp-usage-messaging-app-users-by-country/">WhatsApp
                    is incredibly popular in the U.K.</a> — the message should not be that U.K. lawmakers are trying to
                weaken WhatsApp’s encryption, but rather that U.K. lawmakers are going to make WhatsApp illegal.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘WhatsApp, Signal, and Other Secure Messaging Platforms Write Open Letter to the UK Government Defending End-to-End Encryption’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/whatsapp-signal-uk-open-letter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Washington Post Analysis of the Content That Trained Google’s ‘C4’ LLM Data Set</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/interactive/2023/ai-chatbot-learning/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urd"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/wapo-google-c4"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39865</id>
        <published>2023-04-19T23:09:20Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-19T23:09:21Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>The Washington Post:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Tech companies have grown secretive about what they feed the AI.
                    So The Washington Post set out to analyze one of these data sets
                    to fully reveal the types of proprietary, personal, and often
                    offensive websites that go into an AI’s training data.</p>

                <p>To look inside this black box, we analyzed <a
                        href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Documenting-the-English-Colossal-Clean-Crawled-Dodge-Sap/40c3327a6ddb0603b6892344509c7f428ab43d81">Google’s
                    C4 data
                    set</a>, a massive snapshot of the contents of 15 million
                    websites that have been used to instruct some high-profile
                    English-language AIs, called large language models, including
                    Google’s T5 and Facebook’s LLaMA. (OpenAI does not disclose what
                    datasets it uses to train the models backing its popular chatbot,
                    ChatGPT).</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Scroll the bottom and they have a tool that lets you search for the ranking of a particular website. <a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/wapo-c4-dataset-daring.png">Daring Fireball is
                #24,293</a>; Kottke.org is right behind at #25,310; Six Colors is #38,783; Stratechery is #57,283.
                MacRumors is way up at #761. <a
                        href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/wapo-c4-dataset-forums.png">MacRumors’s forums are
                    at #45</a>, and Apple Insider’s forums are at #211. The New York Times is #4, and The Washington
                Post itself #11.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Washington Post Analysis of the Content That Trained Google’s ‘C4’ LLM Data Set’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/wapo-google-c4">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>App of the Day: Glucomate</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://glucomate.app/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urb"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/glucomate"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39863</id>
        <published>2023-04-19T21:16:00Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-21T02:52:13Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>New app from developer Zach Simone — an iPhone and Apple Watch app for blood glucose recording, tracking,
                and monitoring. I don’t have diabetes, but I know many people who do or have loved ones who do, and it
                seems hard to overstate how important blood glucose monitoring is. <a
                        href="https://zachsim.one/blog/2023/4/19/introducing-glucomate">Simone, on his blog</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>For over 20 years, I’ve had to monitor my blood glucose every
                    single day. The way in which I monitor it has changed a bit
                    over the years, but the need to stay on top of the readings
                    hasn’t. [...]</p>

                <p>A [continuous glucose monitor] generates a lot of data, and the
                    one I use <a href="https://zachsim.one/blog/2017/12/5/cgm-diaries-day-2">even writes that data to
                        HealthKit</a> (though
                    admittedly with a 3-hour delay). Real-time information is only
                    available via the manufacturers app, unless you’re willing to jump
                    through many hoops. No matter, there’s still a huge amount of data
                    being collected. And it starts to build up. But surely all of this
                    data is good for something. What can we do with it?</p>

                <p>That’s where Glucomate comes in. It’s an app for people who
                    record, track, and monitor their blood glucose and use HealthKit
                    to do it. Glucomate is the app that finally does something with
                    all that data. You can analyse recent readings, spot trends, or go
                    back to any date and view its history. It does all this while
                    trying to look as good as possible. A notable feature is the
                    ability to customise each of the tabs by reordering the displayed
                    data. You can even choose to hide the data that isn’t relevant to you.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>The best apps, almost invariably, come from developers scratching their own itches. It looks to me like
                Simone has made a terrifically practical tool for anyone monitoring their blood glucose levels. If you
                have diabetes or know someone who does, Glucomate seems worth a look.</p>

            <p>(There are <a
                    href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-02-22/apple-watch-blood-glucose-monitor-could-revolutionize-diabetes-care-aapl">rumors</a>
                that future Apple Watch models might integrate sensors that read blood glucose levels continuously and
                non-invasively (read: without puncturing your skin), but that’s just a rumor, and even if it comes to
                pass, diabetics will still need ways to monitor their trends.)</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘App of the Day: Glucomate’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/glucomate">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Four Takeaways From the Dominion v. Fox News Settlement</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/04/18/fox-news-dominion-takeaways/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/urc"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/dominion-fox-news-takeaways"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39864</id>
        <published>2023-04-19T21:15:33Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-19T21:15:34Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Great piece by Aaron Blake for The Washington Post that covers a lot of ground succinctly. This point
                stuck out to me:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Dominion says it’s not done, either, with lawyer Stephen
                    Shackelford saying: “We’ve got some other people who have some
                    accountability coming toward them. And we’ll move right on to the
                    next one.”</p>

                <p>Dominion is also <a
                        href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/06/technology/dominion-voting-mike-lindell-trump.html">suing
                    MyPillow CEO Mike Lindell</a>, who
                    promoted the false <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/elections/?itid=lk_inline_manual_44">election</a>
                    claims on Fox and elsewhere.
                    (Lindell’s fate would also seem to matter greatly to Fox, given
                    that documents in the Dominion case show Fox referring to him as
                    the network’s top advertiser.)</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Part of the way Fox News dug itself such a hole on this matter is that they were satisfying two demands
                at once: their audience wanted to hear these nonsensical lies about the election being rigged, and their
                top advertiser — Lindell — desperately <a
                        href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/02/27/media/dominion-fox-news/index.html">wanted to come on the
                    air to promulgate them</a>.</p>

            <p><strong>See also:</strong> <a
                    href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/media/2023/04/19/fox-news-coverage-dominion-lawsuit/">Elahe
                Izadi’s report for the Post</a> on the one cable news channel that is reporting on this settlement very
                quietly. You’ll never guess which.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Four Takeaways From the Dominion v. Fox News Settlement’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/19/dominion-fox-news-takeaways">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Savings Account Is Half Empty</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apples-new-savings-account-makes-iphones-more-valuable-for-thieves"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ura"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/savings-account-is-half-empty"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39862</id>
        <published>2023-04-19T03:13:59Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-20T00:08:51Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Martin Peers, writing for The Information (paywalled, alas), “Apple’s New Savings Account Makes iPhones
                More Valuable — for Thieves”:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Whether this is smart for consumers depends on whether you’re
                    comfortable having your life ruined if someone steals your iPhone.
                    <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/apple-iphone-security-theft-passcode-data-privacya-basic-iphone-feature-helps-criminals-steal-your-digital-life-cbf14b1a">The
                        Wall Street Journal recently published</a> an excellent
                    report about how iPhone thieves are draining people’s bank
                    accounts. That’s a result of people storing credit cards on Apple
                    Pay and very often keeping photos of sensitive personal documents — passports and drivers’ licenses,
                    for example — on their
                    phones. Some people even write down their passwords in the Notes
                    app on the phone. When you stop to think about it, storing all
                    this stuff on a phone does seem kind of crazy.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>That Wall Street Journal report by Joanna Stern and Nicole Nguyen is indeed excellent (and I still intend
                to follow-up on it here, but still haven’t finished), but Peers makes it sound like all a thief needs to
                empty your bank account is your phone. What the Journal story made clear is that thieves need both your
                phone <em>and</em> your device passcode. That’s a big difference.</p>

            <p>Is the threat serious if a thief obtains both your phone <em>and</em> your device passcode? Very. But so
                long as you’re protective of your passcode, you’re safe overall. Passwords protected in your keychain,
                or even in Notes, are safer than passwords written on paper. You’ve got to store them somewhere.
                Promulgating a message that it’s reckless to put any sensitive information in your phone, even using
                features that are designed to store that information securely, is terrible advice. There’s nothing crazy
                about it. It’s simply worth remembering, at all times, just how much your device passcode is protecting.
            </p>

            <p>And the new <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/apple-card-savings-account">interest-paying
                savings accounts</a> are just an alternative to having your Apple Card cash-back go to your Apple Cash
                account — which pays no interest. So if Peers has successfully spooked any Information readers from
                signing up for these savings accounts, all he’s succeeded in doing is keeping them from earning
                interest. There’s zero difference in security. It’s news for Luddites.</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>This isn’t solely Apple’s doing, of course. Most banks and the
                    like now have phone apps, all of which make people vulnerable. But
                    Apple has encouraged it, going so far as to allow people to store
                    their drivers’ licenses on their iPhones and to <a
                            href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/unlock-your-door-with-a-home-key-iph0dc255875/ios">unlock
                        their front
                        doors</a> with their iPhones. And now there’s this savings account — iPhone thieves must be
                    rubbing their hands in anticipation.</p>

                <p>It’s a little hard to square Apple’s moves in this direction with
                    Apple CEO Tim Cook’s evangelism regarding privacy and tech, not to
                    mention his warnings about the dangers of people using technology
                    too much. [...] Could it be Cook is only concerned about data
                    security and privacy when it comes to social media, a business run
                    by other companies?</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>This is just looking to piss on Apple no matter what the story. A <a
                    href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT213046">digital state ID stored in Apple Wallet</a> is <em>more</em>
                secure than a printed card stored in your physical wallet. If one thief takes my iPhone, and another
                takes my wallet and keys, the first thief needs my device passcode to get anything. The second thief
                instantly knows everything that’s printed on my driver’s license and credit cards — including the
                address of my home, where the keys will unlock the doors. The digitization of banking does carry risks,
                but the pre-digital world of banking revolved around paper checks and signatures.</p>

            <p>There’s nothing hard to square about Apple’s initiative in this regard at all. I’ll bet Tim Cook <s>has
                his driver’s license in Apple Wallet</s> — and I practically guarantee that he has his credit cards in
                Apple Wallet. Apple Wallet really is more secure that a physical wallet and cards. And the new savings
                accounts simply offer Apple Card customers a way to earn interest on cash accounts that heretofore did
                not pay any interest at all. There’s nothing to be cynical about with this.</p>

            <p>[<strong>Update:</strong> California isn’t on the very short list of states that currently support IDs in
                Apple Wallet — it’s still just Arizona, Colorado, and Maryland. But my point stands: I’d wager good
                money that as soon as California does support it, Tim Cook will put his ID in Wallet.</p>

            <p>Also, because these savings accounts pay industry-leading interest rates, it’s certain that many people
                will transfer more money into them than they would with regular Apple Cash accounts, which means more
                money is at risk if a thief obtains their phone <em>and</em> device passcode.]</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘The Savings Account Is Half Empty’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/savings-account-is-half-empty">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Fox News Settles With Dominion for $787 Million, Averting Defamation Trial Over Its 2020 Election
            Lies</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/04/18/media/fox-dominion-settlement/index.html"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur9"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/fox-news-settles-with-dominion"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39861</id>
        <published>2023-04-19T00:33:15Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-19T02:49:46Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>CNN:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Fox News reached a last-second settlement with Dominion Voting
                    Systems on Tuesday as the case raced toward opening statements,
                    paying more than $787 million to end a colossal two-year legal
                    battle that publicly shredded the right-wing network’s
                    credibility.</p>

                <p>Fox News’ $787.5 million settlement with Dominion Voting Systems
                    is the largest publicly known defamation settlement in US history
                    involving a media company. [...]</p>

                <p>The right-wing network said in a statement that it “acknowledge[s]
                    the Court’s rulings finding certain claims about Dominion to be
                    false,” referring to <a
                            href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/03/31/media/fox-news-dominion-lawsuit/index.html">Davis’
                        recent ruling</a> that 20 Fox
                    News broadcasts from late 2020 contained blatantly untrue
                    assertions that Dominion rigged the presidential election. But Fox
                    won’t have to admit on-air that it spread lies about Dominion, a
                    Dominion representative told CNN.</p>

                <p>The $787.5 million payout is roughly half of the $1.6 billion that
                    Dominion <a
                            href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/03/26/media/dominion-voting-systems-fox-news-lawsuit/index.html">initially
                        sought</a>, though it is nearly 10 times
                    the company’s valuation from 2018, and roughly eight times its
                    annual revenue in 2021, according to court filings.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>What a <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-64886188">gift to humanity</a> this lawsuit has
                been.</p>

            <p>On the face of it, it makes no sense that anyone still watches Fox News. But that assumes that people
                choose their news sources based on trustworthiness and a desire to learn the truth. That’s how and why
                <em>I</em> pick my news sources. It’s probably how and why <em>you</em> do too. But Fox News appeals to
                a whole swath of people who have an entirely different mindset.</p>

            <p>Fox News addicts justify their continuing viewership on the grounds that, more or less, “everyone does
                it” — that MSNBC, CNN, The New York Times, The Washington Post, the BBC, etc. all blatantly lie to their
                viewers/readers in the same way Dominion proved that Fox News lies to its viewers. <em>They’re all liars
                    and thieves, every system is rigged, and everyone in a position of power or authority is
                    crooked.</em> It’s a form of nihilism that, I think, explains exactly how Trump got elected and how
                he still has significant electoral support. If you believe everyone is a corrupt liar, you might as well
                vote for the corrupt liar who (a) is on your side in the culture wars, and (b) wears his corruption and
                dishonesty on his shirtsleeve. And might as well keep watching the cable “news” network that’s on your
                side in the culture wars, proven liars or not.</p>

            <p>Fox is paying <a href="https://twitter.com/NicoleSganga/status/1648465435384504327">a serious price
                here</a>, but I suspect it’s purely financial, not attention.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Fox News Settles With Dominion for $787 Million, Averting Defamation Trial Over Its 2020 Election Lies’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/fox-news-settles-with-dominion">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Adios, Parler</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://variety.com/2023/digital/news/parler-shut-down-new-owner-starboard-twitter-clone-conservatives-1235583709/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur8"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/parler-shut-down"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39860</id>
        <published>2023-04-18T21:09:55Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T21:09:56Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Todd Spangler, reporting for Variety:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Parler, the self-described “uncancelable free-speech social
                    platform” that catered to right-wing users — which was <a
                            href="https://variety.com/2022/digital/news/kanye-west-parler-deal-terminated-1235447337/">nearly
                        acquired by Kanye West last year</a> — has been shut down by its
                    new owner.</p>

                <p>“No reasonable person believes that a Twitter clone just for
                    conservatives is a viable business any more,” Arlington, Va.-based
                    digital media company Starboard <a href="https://parler.com/">said in announcing Friday that it
                        had acquired Parler</a>.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>No reasonable person believes Parler is ever going to successfully rebrand, either, so it’s a curiosity
                what they bought it for. (Also, there’s <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump">at least
                    one</a> unreasonable person who ostensibly believes a Twitter clone just for conservatives is a
                viable business.)</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Adios, Parler’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/parler-shut-down">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The End of Computer Magazines in America</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.technologizer.com/2023/04/15/the-end-of-computer-magazines-in-america/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur7"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/computer-magazines-mccracken"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39859</id>
        <published>2023-04-18T19:43:38Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T19:43:38Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Harry McCracken, writing at Technologizer:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>The April issues of Maximum PC and MacLife are currently on sale
                    at a newsstand near you — assuming there is a newsstand near
                    you. They’re the last print issues of these two venerable
                    computer magazines, both of which date to 1996 (and were
                    originally known, respectively, as Boot and MacAddict). Starting
                    with their next editions, both publications will be available in
                    digital form only.</p>

                <p>But I’m not writing this article because the dead-tree versions of
                    Maximum PC and MacLife are no more. I’m writing it because they
                    were the last two extant U.S. computer magazines that had managed
                    to cling to life until now. With their abandonment of print, the
                    computer magazine era has officially ended. [...]</p>

                <p>I take the loss personally, and not just because computer
                    magazines kept me gainfully employed from 1991-2008. As a junior
                    high student and <a href="https://techland.time.com/2012/08/03/trs-80/">Radio Shack TRS-80
                        fanatic</a>, I bought my
                    first computer magazine in late 1978, three years after Byte
                    invented the category. It was a momentous enough moment in my life
                    that I can tell you what it was (the <a
                            href="https://archive.org/details/creativecomputing-1978-11">November-December 1978 issue
                        of Creative Computing</a>) and where I got it (Harvard Square’s
                    Out of Town News, the same newsstand that had <a
                            href="https://www.technologizer.com/2009/01/02/the-newsstand-that-spawned-microsoft-is-set-to-close/">played
                        a critical
                        role in the founding of Microsoft just four years earlier)</a>.
                    Even before I purchased that Creative Computing , our mailman had
                    misdelivered a neighbor’s copy of Byte to our house, an error I
                    welcomed and did not attempt to correct. From the moment I
                    discovered computer magazines, I loved them almost as much as I
                    loved computers, which is why I ended up working in the field for
                    so long.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>As McCracken himself notes, it’s impossible to overstate the essential role computer magazines played
                before the web. I read Macworld and MacUser cover-to-cover every month. Magazines were how you learned
                to do stuff, how you learned about new applications and new hardware products, how you learned what you
                might want to buy. When I eventually started writing occasional back-page columns for Macworld, it was
                an indescribable thrill.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘The End of Computer Magazines in America’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/computer-magazines-mccracken">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Apple BKC in Mumbai, the First Apple Store in India, Opened Today</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2023/04/apple-bkc-in-mumbai-opens-for-customers-this-tuesday/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur6"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/apple-bkc-india"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39858</id>
        <published>2023-04-18T19:29:37Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T19:29:37Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Looks beautiful. Some architectural details from Apple Newsroom:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Apple BKC features a triangular handcrafted timber ceiling that
                    extends beyond the glass façade to the underside of the exterior
                    canopy, reflecting the unique geometry of the store. Each tile is
                    made from 408 pieces of timber, forming 31 modules per tile with a
                    total of 1,000 tiles that make up the ceiling. There are over
                    450,000 individual timber elements, all of which were assembled in
                    Delhi. Upon entering the store, customers are greeted by two stone
                    walls sourced from Rajasthan and a 14-meter-long stainless steel
                    staircase connecting the ground level and the cantilevered
                    mezzanine.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@ChanceHMiller/110221138059961880">Chance Miller on Mastodon</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Tim Cook reacting to someone who brought a Macintosh SE to the
                    opening of the Apple BKC store in Mumbai today.</p>

                <p>Maybe the happiest I’ve ever seen him.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Those things <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/mac_classic/specs/mac_se.html">weigh 17
                pounds</a>.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Apple BKC in Mumbai, the First Apple Store in India, Opened Today’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/apple-bkc-india">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Apple Card’s Savings Account Is Now Available, Offering 4.15 Percent Interest</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2023/04/apple-cards-new-high-yield-savings-account-is-now-available-offering-a-4-point-15-percent-apy/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur5"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/apple-card-savings-account"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39857</id>
        <published>2023-04-18T19:15:21Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T19:15:22Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Starting today, Apple Card users can choose to grow their Daily
                    Cash rewards with a Savings account from Goldman Sachs, which
                    offers a high-yield APY of 4.15 percent — a rate that’s more
                    than 10 times the national average. With no fees, no minimum
                    deposits, and no minimum balance requirements, users can easily
                    set up and manage their Savings account directly from Apple Card
                    in Wallet. [...]</p>

                <p>Once a Savings account is set up, all future Daily Cash earned by
                    the user will be automatically deposited into the account. The
                    Daily Cash destination can also be changed at any time, and
                    there’s no limit on how much Daily Cash users can earn. To build
                    on their savings even further, users can deposit additional funds
                    into their Savings account through a linked bank account, or from
                    their Apple Cash balance.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p><a href="https://www.investopedia.com/best-high-yield-savings-accounts-4770633">If you shop around</a>,
                you can find some accounts offering closer to 5 percent, but 4.15 is indeed a very good interest rate
                right now. There’s no catch here — it’s simply another reward for having an Apple Card. You just <a
                        href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT213451">sign up in the Wallet app</a>, and boom, your
                cash rewards go into the savings accounts and you start earning interest.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Card’s Savings Account Is Now Available, Offering 4.15 Percent Interest’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/18/apple-card-savings-account">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://l.kolide.co/3JWbXEv"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ur4"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2023/04/kolide_--_zero_trust_for_okta_2"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/feeds/sponsors//11.39856</id>
        <author>
            <name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name>
        </author>
        <published>2023-04-18T03:00:37Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T20:55:02Z</updated>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Here’s an uncomfortable fact: at most companies, employees can download sensitive company data onto any
                device, keep it there forever, and never even know that they’re doing something wrong.</p>

            <p>Kolide’s new report, <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3I7025A">The State of Sensitive Data</a>, shines a
                light on an area of security that is often ignored, but is nevertheless a massive hole in many
                companies’ Zero Trust fortress.</p>

            <p><img
                    src="https://daringfireball.net/martini/images/kolide-survey-results.png"
                    width=600
                    alt="Study results showing that companies have poor policies for requiring user authentication to access sensitive data (65%); prohibiting downloading sensitive data onto personal devices (46%); ensuring plain-text access credentions are not stored on employee devices (38%); setting a specified time period sensitive data can reside on an employee device (16%)."
            /></p>

            <p>These findings are particularly alarming given the overall state of device security. IT teams routinely
                struggle to enforce timely OS updates and patch management, meaning that end users are storing your most
                sensitive data–things like customer records, confidential IP, and plain-text access credentials–on
                devices that are vulnerable to attack.</p>

            <p>This problem has gone unaddressed because until now there hasn’t been a good solution for it. <a
                    href="https://l.kolide.co/3lch4WK">MDM solutions are too blunt an instrument</a> for dealing with
                sensitive data, and <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3DTTpRA">DLP tools are too extreme and invasive</a> for
                most companies. After all, you’re not trying to ban downloads together, nor regard every download as
                suspicious. You’re just trying to make sure employees aren’t keeping data for longer than they need or
                keeping it on an unmanaged or un-secure device.</p>

            <p>Kolide offers a more nuanced approach to setting and enforcing sensitive data policies. </p>

            <p><em>Our premise is simple: if an employee’s device is out of compliance, it can’t access your apps.</em>
            </p>

            <p>Kolide lets admins run queries to detect sensitive data, flag devices that have violated policies, and
                enforce OS and browser updates so vulnerable devices aren’t accessing data.</p>

            <p>Our unique approach makes device compliance part of the authentication process. If a device isn’t
                compliant, users can’t log in to their cloud apps until they’ve fixed the problem. But instead of
                creating more work for IT, Kolide provides instructions so users can get unblocked on their own.</p>

            <p>To learn more and see our product in action, <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3XlSqAq">visit kolide.com</a>.
            </p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Kolide — Zero Trust for Okta’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2023/04/kolide_--_zero_trust_for_okta_2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>[Sponsor] Kolide — Zero Trust for Okta</title></entry>
    <entry>
        <title>‘Headless Body in Topless Bar’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.inquirer.com/opinion/commentary/headless-body-topless-bar-headline-40th-anniversary-20230414.html"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur3"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/headless-body-in-topless-bar"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39855</id>
        <published>2023-04-18T01:50:26Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T01:50:26Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Michael Klein, writing for The Philadelphia Inquirer:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>This month marks the 40th anniversary of a watershed moment in
                    journalism: the publication of the “Headless Body in Topless Bar”
                    headline on the front page of the New York Post. [...]</p>

                <p>Vincent A. Musetto, one of the Post’s managing editors, gets the
                    credit for “Headless Body in Topless Bar.” In a madcap newsroom
                    run largely by owner Rupert Murdoch’s Fleet Street-hardened crew
                    of Brits, Aussies, and Kiwis, Musetto was a real-deal,
                    prototypical New Yorker: brash, zany, unafraid to drop-kick a
                    trash can during a debate.</p>

                <p>From that day, I wanted to work for Vinnie. Two years later, as a
                    pun-loving 25-year-old copy editor at a South Jersey paper, I
                    tried out as a Post sub-editor, designing pages and writing
                    headlines. On the first day of my tryout, the editors sent me a
                    goofy filler story about male dogs being electrocuted by a poorly
                    grounded lamppost. The headline I submitted: “Piss of death.” It
                    ran in exactly one edition before someone pointed out that such a
                    four-letter word in 18-point type might be too much, even for the
                    New York Post, which five years before had paid a morgue worker to
                    unzip John Lennon’s body bag and take a photo of the slain Beatle
                    in repose.</p>

                <p>Musetto slapped my back, shot me a grin, and offered me a job.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>The best detail: the Post got two sources to confirm that the bar did indeed feature topless dancing.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘‘Headless Body in Topless Bar’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/headless-body-in-topless-bar">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Play — Watch Later App for YouTube (and Other) Videos</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/id1596506190"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur2"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/play"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39854</id>
        <published>2023-04-17T23:18:39Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-17T23:19:45Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Another deceptively simple, very well-crafted app I’ve been meaning to recommend: Play, a “watch later”
                app by <a href="https://marcosatanaka.com/">Marcos Tanaka</a>. Play is a great native app on iOS and
                Mac, and includes a Share sheet extension for adding new videos to your queue. You can categorize videos
                with tags, but that’s not necessary. What I really like is that Play is also a great app on Apple TV. I
                queue videos from my Mac and iPhone, then watch them later on my TV. I like this way better than using
                YouTube itself. One-time purchase of $3 gets you access to Play across all platforms. (That’s too
                cheap — I wish it cost more.)</p>

            <p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2016/12/15/zinc">For years</a> I’d been using an app called <a
                    href="https://zinc.video/">Zinc</a> for the same purpose, but I find myself using Play more than I
                ever used Zinc, because it has a Mac app, and Play’s Share sheet interface is better than Zinc’s
                bookmarklet. Play pulls in all sorts of metadata from YouTube automatically — it’s just great. (Zinc
                still works, if you have it installed, but it appears that the app is no longer available in the App
                Store.)</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Play — Watch Later App for YouTube (and Other) Videos’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/play">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Short Circuit — ChatGPT App for iOS</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://shortcircuit.chat/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur1"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/short-circuit"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39853</id>
        <published>2023-04-17T20:15:29Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T01:57:39Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Developer Joe Fabisevich, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@mergesort@macaw.social/110108604558091308">on
                Mastodon two weeks ago</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>28 days ago I started built a prototype of Siri powered by
                    ChatGPT, and was immediately drawn to the idea of a
                    premium-feeling iOS, iPad, and Mac app for ChatGPT. This amazing
                    technology deserves a good user experience, and we gave it one.</p>

                <p>Partnering with <a href="http://www.mastodon.social/@soroush">@Soroush</a> to make that happen has
                    been a dream,
                    and I’m so excited to share Short Circuit with you.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Very nicely done AI chat app for iOS. Worth checking out for the splendid icon alone — which itself <a
                    href="https://macaw.social/@mergesort/109984019996932151">was crafted by AI</a>. (Short Circuit
                works OK on MacOS via Catalyst, but the developers have a proper Mac app in the works.) If you’re new to
                ChatGPT and aren’t sure what to do, there’s a fun “random prompt” button in the chat input field. The
                integration with Shortcuts means you can just say “Hey Siri, ask Shorty...” and get answers from ChatGPT
                instead of Siri itself. It’s free to try for a limited number of answers; after that, reasonably priced
                subscriptions (ChatGPT is not free):</p>

            <ul>
                <li>$3/month: 100 answers</li>
                <li>$6/month: 300 answers</li>
                <li>$15/month: 1,000 answers</li>
            </ul>

            <p>They also offer a $30 lifetime unlock, if you have your own OpenAI developer token.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Short Circuit — ChatGPT App for iOS’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/short-circuit">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Magic Highlighter Safari Extension</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://themagichighlighter.com/blog/introducing-the-magic-highlighter/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ur0"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/the-magic-highlighter"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39852</id>
        <published>2023-04-17T19:19:47Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-17T19:19:48Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>$2 Safari extension from Caleb Hailey:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>The Magic Highlighter is a brand new <a
                        href="https://themagichighlighter.com/blog/safari-extensions">Safari Extension</a> that
                    automatically highlights your Google.com, DuckDuckGo.com, and
                    Bing.com search terms <em>and phrases</em> on search result web pages — saving you time, and helping
                    you find what you’ve been searching
                    for. The Magic Highlighter is available to download for iPhone,
                    iPad, and Mac. It’s easy to use thanks to direct integration with
                    Safari — just install the app, enable the extension, and use
                    Safari like you normally would.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Clever and simple. In addition to highlighting terms you entered from a search engine, you can highlight
                whatever terms you want on any page, via the extension’s toolbar button.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘The Magic Highlighter Safari Extension’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/the-magic-highlighter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>DPReview Is Working on Some Sort of ‘Archive’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.dpreview.com/news/0507902613/dpreview-closure-an-update"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqz"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/dpreview-update"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39851</id>
        <published>2023-04-17T17:56:48Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-17T18:42:18Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Scott Everett, general manager of the <a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/03/22/amazon-layoffs-dpreview">soon</a>-to-<a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/03/23/coldeway-dpreview">close</a> Amazon subsidiary
                DPReview:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>We’ve received a lot of questions about what’s next for the site.
                    We hear your concerns about losing the content that has been
                    carefully curated over the years, and want to assure you that the
                    content will remain available as an archive.</p>

                <p>We’ve also heard that you need more time to access the site, so
                    we’re going to keep publishing some more stories while we work on
                    archiving.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>I don’t understand either of these paragraphs. I mean, I’m glad they’re still publishing new content, but
                I don’t understand what publishing new stories has to do with giving readers more time to access the
                site. And it’s completely unclear what sort of “archive” is going to be available after it closes.</p>

            <p>What I’d really like to see is for Amazon to change its mind, and keep DPReview going. Or sell it to
                someone else who will. But if it’s going to close, the right way to “archive” it is simply to keep the
                site as-is and make it read-only. When you search for reviews of a specific camera model, DPReview’s
                articles are always at or near the top in the results. Keep those old URLs available, unchanged.</p>

            <p>As for that new content, here’s a good one: <a
                    href="https://www.dpreview.com/articles/5191963353/most-significant-cameras-of-the-dpreview-era-part-1">a
                look back at the most significant cameras DPReview has reviewed over the last 25 years</a>. Remember <a
                    href="https://www.dpreview.com/articles/5191963353/most-significant-cameras-of-the-dpreview-era-part-1?slide=3">the
                Nikons that looked like this</a>? I owned <a
                    href="https://www.dpreview.com/articles/5191963353/most-significant-cameras-of-the-dpreview-era-part-1?slide=9">this
                one</a> and <a
                    href="https://www.dpreview.com/articles/2137384734/most-significant-cameras-of-the-dpreview-era-part-2?slide=3">this
                one</a>, both purchased in part because of DPReview’s review.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘DPReview Is Working on Some Sort of ‘Archive’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/17/dpreview-update">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Meh</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://meh.com/go/df"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqy"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/16/meh"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39850</id>
        <published>2023-04-16T18:51:59Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-16T18:52:00Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>My thanks to Meh for sponsoring last week at DF, and for having a logo that looks so good against DF’s
                background color. Meh sells shit you can buy everywhere. But they’ve got it cheaper than anywhere.
                That’s the deal.</p>

            <p>If you like endless selection, unbelievable promotions, hip marketing, and non-stop hype, go somewhere
                else.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Meh’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/16/meh">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Montana Passes Bill Blocking Users From Downloading TikTok</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/internet/montana-passes-bill-blocking-users-downloading-tiktok-rcna79622"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqx"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/14/montana-tiktok-ban"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39849</id>
        <published>2023-04-15T01:36:13Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-16T18:50:22Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Uwa Ede-Osifo, reporting for NBC News:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Montana lawmakers passed a bill Friday blocking downloads of TikTok, the most significant action yet
                    by a state yet against the app. The bill, <a
                            href="https://leg.mt.gov/bills/2023/billhtml/SB0419.htm">SB 419</a>, makes it illegal for
                    app stores to give users the option to download the app and also illegal for the company to operate
                    within the state. The bill does not, however, make it illegal for people who already have TikTok to
                    use the app. A previous version of the bill sought to force internet providers to block TikTok, but
                    that language was later removed.</p>

                <p>The bill passed by a vote of 54-43.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Putting aside the fact that Montana is a small state (44th in population, 1.1 million people), it just
                doesn’t seem feasible to ban TikTok at the state level. Even if this goes into law and Apple and Google
                comply, Montanans can just cross state lines to download it. And what constitutes a “download”? When you
                buy a new phone and restore from your backup, your phone re-downloads all the apps you had installed on
                your old phone. Does this mean Montanans who already have TikTok will lose it if they buy a new device,
                or restore their current one?</p>

            <p>I do think the U.S. should ban TikTok nationwide. But it seems futile — silly even — for states to do it
                piecemeal.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Montana Passes Bill Blocking Users From Downloading TikTok’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/14/montana-tiktok-ban">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Print Editions of ‘Make Something Wonderful’ for Sale on eBay</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.ebay.com/sch/i.html?_from=R40&amp;_trksid=p4432023.m570.l1313&amp;_nkw=make+something+wonderful&amp;_sacat=0"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqw"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/14/make-something-wonderful-ebay"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39848</id>
        <published>2023-04-14T11:58:19Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-15T02:18:29Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/shareware-heroes">Speaking of books</a>, print
                copies of the Steve Jobs Archive’s <a href="https://stevejobsarchive.com/book"><em>Make Something
                    Wonderful: Steve Jobs in His Own Words</em></a> — presumably copies given to folks at Apple and
                Disney — have hit eBay. Prices are really high — $500–1,000.</p>

            <p>The website edition is a fantastic experience — <a
                    href="https://twitter.com/mike_matas/status/1645790693758242819">thoughtfully designed</a>, and <a
                    href="https://twitter.com/lorenb">implemented with handcrafted care</a> — but I do wish the SJA had
                made the print edition available for retail purchase by the public. (I get it that the SJA doesn’t want
                to monetize this stuff, but they could sell these books and donate the proceeds to charities that
                Laurene Powell Jobs is involved with.)</p>

            <p>I’ve lucked my way into a copy, and it’s as nice an object as you’d expect. Books can be such lovely
                artifacts in hand, tactile experiences, and this is one. The whole thing — web and print editions
                alike — is exemplary work from LoveFrom.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Print Editions of ‘Make Something Wonderful’ for Sale on eBay’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/14/make-something-wonderful-ebay">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>‘Shareware Heroes’ by Richard Moss</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sharewareheroes.com/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqv"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/shareware-heroes"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39847</id>
        <published>2023-04-14T02:35:21Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-14T11:52:53Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>From Richard Moss, author of the excellent <a href="https://secrethistoryofmacgaming.com/"><em>The Secret
                History of Mac Gaming</em></a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p><em>Shareware Heroes</em> takes readers on a journey through a critical
                    yet long overlooked chapter in video game history: the rise and
                    eventual fall of the shareware model.</p>

                <p>As commercial game distribution professionalised in the 1980s,
                    independent creators with scant resources or contacts were
                    squeezed out of the market. But not entirely. New technologies and
                    distribution concepts were creating a hidden games publishing
                    market — one that operated by different rules and that, at least
                    for the first several years, had no powerful giants.</p>

                <p>It was a land of opportunity and promise, and a glimpse of the
                    digital-first future. This is the story of the games and
                    developers who relied on nascent networking technologies combined
                    with word-of-mouth marketing in an era before social media.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>What a fun website Moss made for this. It’s just perfect. He’s got <a
                    href="https://sharewareheroes.com/doomed.html">a preview from the chapter on Id Software’s Doom</a>
                to whet your appetite. The book is available in hardcover, paperback, audio book, and e-book formats.
            </p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘‘Shareware Heroes’ by Richard Moss’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/shareware-heroes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>IDC: PC Sales, Including Macs, Are Way Down From a Year Ago</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS50565723"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqu"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/idc-pc-sales-slump"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39846</id>
        <published>2023-04-13T22:49:01Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-13T22:49:02Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>IDC:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Weak demand, excess inventory, and a worsening macroeconomic
                    climate were all contributing factors for the precipitous drop in
                    shipments of traditional PCs during the first quarter of 2023
                    (1Q23). Global shipments numbered 56.9 million, marking a
                    contraction of 29.0% compared to the same quarter in 2022,
                    according to preliminary results from the International Data
                    Corporation (IDC) <a href="https://www.idc.com/tracker/showproductinfo.jsp?containerId=IDC_P36344">Worldwide
                        Quarterly Personal Computing Device
                        Tracker</a>.</p>

                <p>The preliminary results also represented a coda to the era of
                    COVID-driven demand and at least a temporary return to pre-COVID
                    patterns. Shipment volume in 1Q23 was noticeably lower than the
                    59.2 million units shipped in 1Q19 and 60.6 million in 1Q18.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>According to IDC, Windows PC sales are down about 30 percent for the first quarter, year-over-year, and
                Mac sales are down 40 percent. Are IDC’s numbers accurate? We should get a sense of that when Apple
                announces results for the January–March quarter on May 4.</p>

            <p>But we’ve already seen how strong the pull-forward effect from COVID and work-from-home has been: for the
                October–December 2022 quarter, <a
                        href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/pdfs/FY23_Q1_Consolidated_Financial_Statements.pdf">Mac
                    revenue was down 31 percent</a>. And most strikingly, Apple had a record-breaking quarter for Mac
                sales <a
                        href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2020/10/apple-q4-2020-results-record-mac-revenue-iphone-down/">in
                    the July–September quarter of 2020</a> — <em>after</em> Apple had announced the transition to Apple
                Silicon at WWDC, but months before those much-anticipated Macs shipped. People buy new PCs when they
                need them, and zillions of people needed new PCs during COVID and with the post-COVID continuing
                transition to more work from home.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘IDC: PC Sales, Including Macs, Are Way Down From a Year Ago’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/idc-pc-sales-slump">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>InsideSticker</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://insidesticker.com/en-us"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqt"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/insidesticker"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39845</id>
        <published>2023-04-13T22:02:31Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-13T22:02:31Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>An idea so grotesque that it’s awesome: exquisitely designed holographic “Inside” stickers for Apple’s
                M-series chips. From the talented but obviously twisted mind of <a
                        href="https://twitter.com/helvetiica">Vinoth Ragunathan</a>.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘InsideSticker’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/13/insidesticker">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://meh.com/go/df"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/uqs"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2023/04/meh_1"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/feeds/sponsors//11.39844</id>
        <author>
            <name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name>
        </author>
        <published>2023-04-13T21:02:08Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-13T21:02:16Z</updated>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>We’re selling shit you can buy everywhere. But we’ve got it cheaper than anywhere. That’s the deal.</p>

            <p>If you like endless selection, unbelievable promotions, hip marketing and non-stop hype, go somewhere
                else.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Meh.com’" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2023/04/meh_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>[Sponsor] Meh.com</title></entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/warner_max"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/uqr"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023://1.39843</id>
        <published>2023-04-12T21:56:34Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-13T20:51:51Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <summary type="text">HBO’s new slogan might as well be “It’s not TV. It’s a tab somewhere in the Max app.”
        </summary>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p><a href="https://press.wbd.com/us/media-release/warner-bros-discovery-unveils-max-streaming-service">Warner
                Bros. Discovery</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Warner Bros. Discovery today introduced Max, its enhanced
                    streaming service, which will launch in the U.S. on May 23. Max is
                    the destination for HBO Originals, Warner Bros. films, Max
                    Originals, the DC universe, the Wizarding World of Harry Potter,
                    an expansive offering of kids content, and best-in-class
                    programming across food, home, reality, lifestyle and
                    documentaries from leading brands like HGTV, Food Network,
                    Discovery Channel, TLC, ID and more. Max will stand out amongst
                    streamers by uniquely combining unrivaled breadth and superior
                    quality with iconic franchises and strong product experience, all
                    for great value.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>I would argue the opposite: that by cramming their entire disparate gamut of brands into a single
                service, none of them stand out, and the Max brand stands for nothing.<sup id="fnr1-2023-04-12"><a
                        href="#fn1-2023-04-12">1</a></sup></p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Max will offer three pricing options, giving subscribers the
                    choice to select which plan best fits the needs of their
                    household.</p>

                <ul>
                    <li>Max Ad-Lite — $9.99/month or $99.99/year <br/>
                        2 concurrent streams, 1080p resolution, no offline downloads,
                        5.1 surround sound quality
                    </li>
                    <li>Max Ad Free — $15.99/month or $149.99/year <br/>
                        2 concurrent streams, 1080 resolution, 30 offline downloads, 5.1 surround
                        sound quality
                    </li>
                    <li>Max Ultimate Ad Free — $19.99/month or $199.99/year <br/>
                        4 concurrent streams, up to 4K UHD resolution, 100 offline
                        downloads, Dolby Atmos sound quality
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </blockquote>

            <p>These prices are pretty much the same as <a href="https://www.netflix.com/signup/planform">Netflix’s</a>,
                except that Netflix’s “basic with ads” tier (it’s adorable that Max is calling theirs “ad-lite”) is
                $7/month and, criminally, still limited to 720p resolution. <a
                        href="https://www.disneyplus.com/welcome/disney-hulu-espn-bundle">Disney+</a> currently offers
                two plans: $8/month with ads, or $11/month without (and with offline downloads). Disney+ also offers
                bundles with Hulu and ESPN+: $13/month with ads, $20/month without. Apple TV+ — with a growing but
                admittedly boutique-sized library compared to Max, Netflix, and Disney/Hulu — is $7/month, and has no
                tier with ads.</p>

            <p>When this “Max” name truncation was first rumored in December, <a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/12/06/cnbc-warner-max">I wrote</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Not the worst name they could go with. The mistake with “HBO Max”
                    was muddying the premium HBO brand with the “anything and
                    everything” content of a unified app for everything this enormous
                    content factory conglomerate puts online. My big question is what
                    happens to HBO content. Is it stuck in a tab inside the “Max” app,
                    or will there be a standalone “HBO” app too?</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Looks like HBO is now just a brand inside the Max service. They’re ceding the “everything you get on this
                service is premium content, and there are no ads” ground to Apple TV+. HBO is still HBO on cable, but as
                the world inexorably moves to an all-streaming future, this feels like “corporate synergy” run amok. The
                non-HBO content in HBO Max already diluted the brand; now they’re putting even more non-premium content
                (all the Discovery crap) into the same app. (Today’s New York Times headline says it all: “<a
                        href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/11/business/media/max-streaming-warner-hbo.html">‘Succession’
                    and ‘Dr. Pimple Popper’ Together in New Warner Streaming App</a>”.)</p>

            <p>Disney set the example Warner Bros. Discovery should have followed, with Disney+ and Hulu as separate
                apps, but priced together in a bundle. Disney isn’t relegating Disney+ content into a mere tab in the
                Hulu app, nor are they allowing Hulu’s content to dilute the prestigious Disney brand in the Disney+
                app.</p>

            <p>They obviously think they’ve being clever with <a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/max-logotype.jpeg">the Max logotype</a> having a dot
                inside the “a”, evoking the “o” in HBO’s, but I find it just sad — the bastardization of an iconic mark.
                Either Max stands on its own, independent of HBO, or HBO should be <em>the</em> brand for HBO content.
            </p>

            <p>HBO’s old slogan was “It’s not TV. It’s HBO”. That slogan captured HBO’s prestige: unedited major motion
                pictures, best-of-breed original content, all without commercial interruptions. HBO’s new slogan might
                as well be “It’s not TV. It’s a tab somewhere in the Max app.”</p>

            <div class="footnotes">
                <hr/>
                <ol>
                    <li id="fn1-2023-04-12">
                        <p>The nomenclatural trend <em>du jour</em> for subscription services is to take your company’s
                            existing well-known brand and tack on a suffix like <em>plus</em>, <em>max</em>, or
                            <em>one</em>. Hence: Disney+, ESPN+, Paramount+, Apple TV+, Apple One, Google One — <a
                                    href="https://www.canalplus.com/">even Canal+ in France</a>. I think that’s what
                            Warner was going for with the “Max” in HBO Max. So in some sense going with just plain “Max”
                            makes no more branding sense than if Disney+ or Paramount+ had been named just “Plus”. But
                            for those of you my age or older, <em>Max</em> also brings to mind Cinemax — Warner’s
                            longtime cable-pay-channel sibling to HBO. Premium and commercial-free, like HBO, but
                            clearly not <em>as</em> premium. HBO is <a
                                    href="https://www.baseball-reference.com/players/d/dimagjo01.shtml">Joe DiMaggio</a>;
                            Cinemax is <a href="https://www.baseball-reference.com/players/d/dimagdo01.shtml">Dom
                                DiMaggio</a>. HBO is the home of hall-of-fame groundbreaking original series like <em>The
                                Sopranos</em>, <em>The Wire</em>, <em>The Larry Sanders Show</em>, <em>Curb Your
                                Enthusiasm</em>, <em>Game of Thrones</em>, and <em>Succession</em>. Cinemax is the home
                            of ... <a href="https://www.imdb.com/list/ls567109928/">checks notes</a> ...
                            <em>Banshee</em>, <em>The Knick</em>, <em>Warrior</em>, and <em>Mike Judge Presents: Tales
                                from the Tour Bus</em>. Cinemax’s biggest claim to fame from my teenage years is that
                            after a certain hour, they showed movies that earned them the nickname “<a
                                    href="https://screencrush.com/rip-skinemax/">Skinemax</a>”. (Sleepovers were always
                            preferably held at the homes of Cinemax subscribers.)</p>

                        <p>No matter what Warner Bros. Discovery intends “Max” to mean, it feels damn stupid to lean
                            even vaguely on Cinemax, and not at all on HBO, as a brand name.&nbsp;<a
                                    href="#fnr1-2023-04-12" class="footnoteBackLink"
                                    title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </div>


            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>★ Warner Bros. Discovery Is Really Going to Drop the ‘HBO’ Brand and Just Call Its Streaming Service
            ‘Max’</title></entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Bob Iger’s Letter to Disney Employees Accompanying Their Copies of ‘Make Something Wonderful’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/iger-disney-jobs-book-letter.jpeg"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqq"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/12/iger-jobs-book-letter"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39842</id>
        <published>2023-04-12T16:12:54Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-12T18:00:29Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Bob Iger, in a company-wide memo:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>What makes it different is that it is a collection of Steve’s own
                    words, drawn from his speeches, interviews, and correspondence. In
                    these pages, we are offered a glimpse into his unique and
                    wonderful mind. In a sense, this book is another tool from Steve — a resource for you, the reader,
                    to spark the creativity that
                    lives inside all of us and make your own mark on the world.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>My link on this post is to a photo of the letter, via a little birdie at Disney — here’s <a
                    href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/iger-disney-jobs-book-letter.text">the text of the
                letter</a>, and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/110187006998782806">my post on Mastodon</a>.
            </p>

            <p>Also, for everyone enjoying the book on the website, due to a regression in the latest version of
                Safari/WebKit, it works best in Chromium browser. (Example: the full-screen pages lock into place as you
                swipe.)</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Bob Iger’s Letter to Disney Employees Accompanying Their Copies of ‘Make Something Wonderful’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/12/iger-jobs-book-letter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>‘Make Something Wonderful: Steve Jobs in His Own Words’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stevejobsarchive.com/book"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqp"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/11/make-something-wonderful"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39841</id>
        <published>2023-04-11T20:34:58Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-11T20:34:59Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>New, from The Steve Jobs Archive:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>A curated collection of Steve’s speeches, interviews and
                    correspondence, Make Something Wonderful offers an unparalleled
                    window into how one of the world’s most creative entrepreneurs
                    approached his life and work. In these pages, Steve shares his
                    perspective on his childhood, on launching and being pushed out of
                    Apple, on his time with Pixar and NeXT, and on his ultimate return
                    to the company that started it all.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>From Laurene Powell Jobs’s introduction:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Steve once told a group of students, “You appear, have a chance to
                    blaze in the sky, then you disappear.” He gave an extraordinary
                    amount of thought to how best to use our fleeting time. He was
                    compelled by the notion of being part of the arc of human
                    existence, animated by the thought that he — or that any of us — might elevate or expedite human
                    progress.</p>

                <p>It is hard enough to see what is already there, to gain a clear
                    view. Steve’s gift was greater still: he saw clearly what was not
                    there, what could be there, what had to be there. His mind was
                    never a captive of reality. Quite the contrary: he imagined what
                    reality lacked and set out to remedy it. His ideas were not
                    arguments, but intuitions, born of a true inner freedom and an
                    epic sense of possibility.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>There’s a (very?) limited print edition that is not for sale, but is being given to Apple employees and
                others who were close to Jobs (such as Jony Ive’s team at LoveFrom, who clearly produced this work and
                the lovely apple tree logomark). It’s freely available <a href="http://apple.co/sja">on Apple Books</a>
                (nice URL), but I think the best way to read it, if you’re not fortunate enough to have access to the
                printed book, is the website. It’s just lovely.</p>

            <p><a href="https://twitter.com/sdw/status/1645833999762472960">Sebastiaan de With, on Twitter</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>It’s hard to capture the delight of a real book, but this website
                    does a fantastic job coming close. Lots delightful, thoughtful
                    little details.</p>

                <p>I say ‘ebook’ because it isn’t a word used anywhere on the
                    website, likely for good reason: there are no good ebooks. The
                    ePub file lacks all the delight of the beautiful website. Books on
                    Apple Books are objectively worse than their written counterparts.
                    This might be nicer.</p>

                <p>Try jumping around using the ‘line of contents’. Super nice stuff.
                    The website even remembers where you left off.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘‘Make Something Wonderful: Steve Jobs in His Own Words’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/11/make-something-wonderful">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Microsoft Now Supports Windows 11 on Apple Silicon Macs, but Only Through Parallels</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/2/16/23602718/microsoft-windows-11-apple-mac-m1-m2-support-parallels-virtual-machines"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqo"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/11/windows-11-apple-silicon"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39840</id>
        <published>2023-04-11T19:46:53Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-11T23:49:41Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Tom Warren, reporting for The Verge back in February:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Still, Microsoft’s plan to officially authorize Parallels to
                    support this way of running Windows 11 on Apple’s latest Macs is a
                    step beyond what we’ve had so far. Up until now, Microsoft has
                    only licensed Windows versions of Arm directly to OEMs, making it
                    difficult for M1 and M2 users to officially run it in VM.</p>

                <p>Parallels started supporting Windows on M1 chips with the
                    Parallels Desktop 16.5 release, but this latest version lets you
                    download and install Windows 11 in a single click. Parallels is
                    also handling the complexity of Windows 11’s TPM and Secure Boot
                    requirements with a virtual TPM that’s paired with Apple silicon.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>It’s nice to be able to run Windows at all on Apple Silicon Macs, but I find it a bit strange that
                Microsoft doesn’t simply allow the direct installation of Windows via Boot Camp, like on Intel Macs. My
                understanding is that Apple would welcome this and work with Microsoft to make it work as well as
                possible, and it’s Microsoft’s decision not to license the ARM version of Windows for direct
                installation on Macs. Note, for example, the existence of <a href="https://asahilinux.org/about/">Asahi
                    Linux</a> — a project that already has a working (although incomplete, driver-wise) version of Linux
                you can install directly on Apple Silicon Macs.</p>

            <p>[<strong>Update:</strong> A little birdie at Microsoft reports that running Windows via Parallels was in
                fact <em>Apple’s</em> preferred solution, and the birdie was left with the impression that Apple does
                not want to support Boot Camp on Apple Silicon Macs. Interesting then, that installing and booting into
                non-Mac OSes — like Asahi Linux — is supported at all. You certainly can’t do that with iPhones or iPads
                or Apple TVs.]</p>

            <p>For people who need or just want to run Windows on their Macs: how well does it work going through
                Parallels? As everyone now knows, MacOS running on Apple Silicon hardware runs both faster <em>and</em>
                more efficiently (longer battery life) than it does on Intel hardware. Does practical day-to-day usage
                of Windows, through Parallels, running on Apple Silicon hardware show similar performance and battery
                life gains? I would imagine that some, but not all, of MacOS’s efficiency on Apple Silicon comes from
                having the entire OS tuned not just for ARM CPUs in general but <a
                        href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/11/the_m1_macs#bespoke-architecture">for Apple’s M-series
                    SoCs specifically</a>. Anyone out there who’s using this, <a
                        href="https://daringfireball.net/contact/">let me know</a>.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Microsoft Now Supports Windows 11 on Apple Silicon Macs, but Only Through Parallels’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/11/windows-11-apple-silicon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>‘Katie Knows Everything’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2014/05/katie_cotton"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqn"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/11/katie-knows-everything"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39839</id>
        <published>2023-04-11T19:23:59Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-11T19:23:59Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>From the DF archive, my piece in 2014 remarking upon her retirement from Apple, with an anecdote from the
                iPhone 4 “antennagate” press conference in 2010:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>I was wearing a large SLR camera on a strap around my neck. As I
                    filed in to find a seat, I was offered a choice: if I wanted to
                    take photos during the event, I could sit toward the back; if I
                    were willing to forgo taking photos, I could sit up front in the
                    third row. I only had my camera with me on a lark — the
                    advantages of publishing a website that runs photographs only
                    rarely — so I took the seat in the third row. The first two rows,
                    as usual, were occupied by senior Apple executives and employees.</p>

                <p>As I took my seat, Katie Cotton, sitting in the second row, smiled
                    and greeted me. “Hi John, glad you could make it. How’s the cold?”</p>

                <p>I was feeling fine, the cold not much more than a memory at that
                    point, and told her so. But I had to ask, laughing, “How did you
                    even know I had a cold?”</p>

                <p>Before she could answer, <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=greg%20joswiak">Greg Joswiak</a>,
                    sitting directly in
                    front of me, turned around. “John, Katie knows <em>everything</em>.”</p>
            </blockquote>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘‘Katie Knows Everything’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/11/katie-knows-everything">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Kara Swisher on Katie Cotton</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.vox.com/2014/5/30/11627500/goodbye-to-all-that-today-is-katie-cottons-last-day-at-apple"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqm"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/swisher-on-cotton"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39838</id>
        <published>2023-04-11T01:50:03Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-11T02:45:09Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Kara Swisher, back in 2014, on Katie Cotton’s retirement from Apple:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Did she sometimes ice our reporters out, ignore calls or reply
                    with newsless answers? Sometimes. [...] Did she try her hardest
                    to showcase Apple and its products in a way that benefited it?
                    Yep. [...] Was she vocal when she did not like something we did?
                    And how.</p>

                <p><em>So what?</em></p>

                <p>That kind of hard driving is part and parcel to the business, even
                    if she was harder driving and, because of that, more successful
                    than most. As she once told me when we talked about her outsize
                    reputation in the tech press: “I am not here to make friends with
                    reporters, I am here to put a light on and sell Apple products.”</p>

                <p>It was no surprise that some used the opportunity of her exit to
                    drag out their complaints in the kind of strange rage that has
                    been — at least to my mind — oddly emotional and sometimes full
                    of vitriol that would never be directed at a man who was
                    similarly strong.</p>

                <p>Consider the various words used to describe her: “Queen of Evil,”
                    “wicked witch,” “cold and distant,” “frigid supremacy,” “queen
                    bee” and, perhaps most obviously misogynistic, “dominatrix.”</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>I always appreciated Cotton’s forthrightness, and part of that is Apple’s institutional default to “no
                comment” when asked about anything other than what Apple wants to talk about. Those “no comments” seem
                to downright offend some reporters, but to me, they’re a sign of respect. Better not to say anything at
                all, and waste no one’s time, than to offer up a lengthy but meaningless pile of bullshit, which in my
                experience is how most PR teams operate. If you wanted Katie Cotton to coddle you or bullshit you for an
                hour, you were going to be disappointed. If you wanted Katie Cotton to respect you, you simply needed to
                respect her and her team at Apple.</p>

            <p>As for the misogyny she faced at every step of her career, a lasting part of Cotton’s legacy is that
                Apple’s PR team remains full of women. I’d wager that Apple PR is majority women, in fact. I could
                contact Apple to ask about that, but I think I know the answer I’d get.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Kara Swisher on Katie Cotton’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/swisher-on-cotton">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Katie Cotton, Rest in Peace</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://obits.lehighvalleylive.com/us/obituaries/etpa/name/kathryn-cotton-obituary?id=51601641"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uql"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/katie-cotton-rip"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39837</id>
        <published>2023-04-10T23:56:39Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-10T23:56:39Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Terribly sad news: former Apple PR leader Katie Cotton has died, apparently after a long illness:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>It is with great sadness that the family of Kathryn Elizabeth
                    Cotton announces her passing. Fondly known to family, friends and
                    all who loved her as Katie. She passed peacefully on Thursday
                    evening, April 6, surrounded by family and close friends. [...]</p>

                <p>Katie is recognized as one of the most remarkable women in Public
                    Relations and Marketing in Technology. In her role as Vice
                    President of Worldwide Corporate Communications for Apple Inc.,
                    she worked most of her 18-year career directly for Steve Jobs. She
                    was a strong and unwavering proponent for the company, helping to
                    elevate its products and brand.</p>

                <p>If you would like to honor Katie’s life and charitable work,
                    please consider a donation to <a href="https://www.petsinneed.org/">Pets In
                        Need</a> in Redwood City or
                    <a href="https://safespace.org/">SafeSpace</a> in Menlo Park.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Katie Cotton, Rest in Peace’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/katie-cotton-rip">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ostensibly Private Twitter Circle Tweets Are Being Shown Publicly</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/04/10/twitter-circle-bug-not-private/?guccounter=1"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqk"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/twitter-circle"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39836</id>
        <published>2023-04-10T23:34:01Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-10T23:34:02Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Amanda Silberling, writing for TechCrunch:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Numerous Twitter users are reporting a bug in which Circle tweets — which are supposed to reach a
                    select group, like an Instagram
                    <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/11/30/how-instagram-close-friends-works/">Close Friends</a>
                    story — are surfacing on the
                    algorithmically generated <a
                            href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/24/twitter-wont-force-you-to-the-for-you-timeline-on-web-anymore/">For
                        You</a> timeline. That means
                    that your supposedly private posts might breach containment to
                    reach an unintended audience, which could quickly spark some
                    uncomfortable situations.</p>

                <p>I observed this bug when a tweet from someone I follow appeared on
                    my For You timeline, but the retweet button was disabled, despite
                    the person’s account being public. When I clicked on the tweet, it
                    disappeared. I asked the tweeter if that post was intended for
                    their Circle — which I am not in — and they confirmed this was
                    the case. [...]</p>

                <p>TechCrunch has spoken to multiple users who have also experienced
                    this glitch firsthand; <a href="https://twitter.com/adamjmoussa/status/1644460901779615745">many</a>
                    <a href="https://twitter.com/AC3ATTORN3Y/status/1644526438786146304">more</a> <a
                            href="https://twitter.com/ERnurse86/status/1644733902840365060">have</a>
                    <a href="https://twitter.com/DaricCott/status/1644541029641752578">reported</a> the glitch in their
                    tweets. Most often, it seems
                    that Circle tweets are being surfaced in the For You timeline to
                    users who follow the poster, but are not in their Circle. Others
                    have reported that their Circle tweets are reaching even further
                    than those who follow them.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Other privacy-related bugs I’ve seen people mention recently:</p>

            <ul>
                <li><a href="https://twitter.com/WillOremus/status/1639297936499658753">Will Oremus saw tweets in his
                    timeline from people who had blocked him</a>.
                </li>
                <li>Ian Coldwater, testing the privacy of Twitter Circles, created a circle with just one other person,
                    sent a tweet to that circle, <a href="https://twitter.com/IanColdwater/status/1645468617394331649">and
                        it was shown to several people not in the circle</a>.
                </li>
                <li>Replying to Coldwater, <a href="https://twitter.com/wbm312/status/1645497243708067841">Whitney
                    Merrill argues that this is a data breach under EU law</a>, and could result in hefty fines.
                </li>
            </ul>

            <p>I don’t trust anything “private” about Twitter, including and especially DMs. Some kind of breach
                regarding DMs seems inevitable at this point, given how sloppy Twitter is getting under Phony Stark.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Ostensibly Private Twitter Circle Tweets Are Being Shown Publicly’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/twitter-circle">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>CGP Grey Grades America’s State Flags</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l4w6808wJcU"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqj"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/cgp-grey-americas-flags"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39835</id>
        <published>2023-04-10T21:29:39Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-10T21:29:40Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>I love CGP Grey’s videos, and I know firsthand that we largely share similar design taste. (At some
                long-ago WWDC in San Francisco, Grey and I realized we carried not only <a
                        href="https://bellroy.com/products/card-sleeve-wallet">the exact same wallet</a>, but the same
                (alas, now discontinued) <em>color</em> of that wallet.) So I expected to largely agree with his grading
                of the 50 American state flags. I did not expect to agree with his grades completely. 50 for 50, no
                notes.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘CGP Grey Grades America’s State Flags’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/cgp-grey-americas-flags">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>‘The Real-World Costs of the Digital Race for Bitcoin’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/09/business/bitcoin-mining-electricity-pollution.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&amp;referringSource=articleShare"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqi"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/nyt-costs-of-bitcoin"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39834</id>
        <published>2023-04-10T21:12:40Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-10T21:12:41Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Gabriel J.X. Dance, reporting for The New York Times (with informative graphics by Tim Wallace and Zach
                Levitt) on the Bitcoin mining industry:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>It is as if another New York City’s worth of residences were now
                    drawing on the nation’s power supply, The Times found.</p>

                <p>In some areas, this has led prices to surge. In Texas, where 10 of
                    the 34 mines are connected to the state’s grid, the increased
                    demand has caused electric bills for power customers to rise
                    nearly 5 percent, or $1.8 billion per year, according to a
                    simulation performed for The Times by the energy research and
                    consulting firm Wood Mackenzie.</p>

                <p>The additional power use across the country also causes as much
                    carbon pollution as adding 3.5 million gas-powered cars to
                    America’s roads, according to an analysis by WattTime, a nonprofit
                    tech company. Many of the Bitcoin operations promote themselves as
                    environmentally friendly and set up in areas rich with renewable
                    energy, but their power needs are far too great to be satisfied by
                    those sources alone. As a result, they have become a boon for the
                    fossil fuel industry: WattTime found that coal and natural gas
                    plants kick in to meet 85 percent of the demand these Bitcoin
                    operations add to their grids.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>The costs of Bitcoin seem clear: higher energy prices and more carbon emissions. Totally unclear: what we
                should, or even can, do about it.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Real-World Costs of the Digital Race for Bitcoin’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/10/nyt-costs-of-bitcoin">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/gm_carplay_iphones"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/uqh"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023://1.39833</id>
        <published>2023-04-10T21:01:49Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-11T02:14:20Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <summary type="text">In many ways our phones are our new digital hubs, and CarPlay exemplifies that role.
        </summary>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Jason Snell, writing at Six Colors, “<a
                    href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2023/04/general-motors-hates-your-iphone/">General Motors Hates
                Your iPhone</a>”:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>I get the impulse to want to control everything that happens in
                    your car, if you’re an automaker. But given the fact that the
                    smartphone is everyone’s <em>real</em> ride-or-die, the best choice is to
                    integrate tightly with the supercomputer we all keep in our
                    pockets, not to say “let them eat Bluetooth” and be happy
                    degrading the customer experience in the interest of control and
                    incremental revenue. [...]</p>

                <p>Will GM’s competitors follow its lead, relieved that the world is
                    finally starting to trend away from bring-your-own-device support
                    in cars? Or will they consider CarPlay a competitive advantage
                    that will allow them to market their own vehicles against GM’s? I
                    sure hope it’s the latter, because we’re never going to give up
                    our smartphones — and if our cars don’t talk to them properly,
                    our in-car experiences will always be second-rate.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>One thought I had regarding this decision by GM is that it’s a bit like selling “smart” TV sets that
                don’t support HDMI input. You get the TV maker’s interface for using apps, games, and streaming
                services, with no choice to plug in a third-party device like an Apple TV, Chromecast stick, or Roku. I
                don’t know of any TV sets like that, but HomePods are sort of like that as speakers. HomePods have no
                traditional line-in for audio — whatever sound comes out of your HomePods, it comes through Apple’s own
                software stack. GM is more like a traditional speaker company. It’d be really weird if, say, Bose sold a
                set of smart speakers that didn’t support line-in, because unlike Apple, Bose isn’t a leading software
                platform company.</p>

            <p>Tesla is seemingly thriving while going its own way software-wise. Rivian is following Tesla’s lead, and
                can’t manufacture their vehicles fast enough to keep up with demand. But both of those companies have
                roots in Silicon Valley, not Detroit. Both Tesla and Rivian seem more like Apple than they do General
                Motors.</p>

            <p>Marques Brownlee had Rivian CEO R.J. Scaringe as his guest on his Waveform podcast this week (recorded in
                the cabin of a Rivian R1S), and asked him about Rivian’s decision not to support CarPlay or Android
                Auto. <a href="https://youtu.be/RdjDDtHvUXA?t=709">Scaringe’s answer (11m:49s) was good</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>“I mean a lot of the things we do, like whether it’s music or
                    mapping, we have to make sure we integrate in with the
                    best-in-class platforms. But by controlling the system it just
                    allows us to be the ... arbiter, the head chef, in terms of the
                    experience that you get, versus handing over control of what we
                    think is one of the most important parts of the experience.”</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Rivian sees itself as much as a software company as a hardware one. That’s an ambitious gamble, to be
                sure, but Scaringe’s comments clearly show that Rivian understands the stakes, and are doing this to put
                the overall driving/ownership experience first.<sup id="fnr1-2023-04-10"><a href="#fn1-2023-04-10">1</a></sup>
            </p>

            <p>The system that runs the onboard computer is a major factor in car-buying decisions today, and it’s only
                increasing in importance with each passing year. If GM, in collaboration with Google, creates their own
                custom platform that makes people as happy as Tesla’s and Rivian’s do, well, OK. But I have no faith in
                GM or Google to pull that off. I personally know several Tesla owners whose number one complaint is that
                Teslas don’t support CarPlay, and I know other people who have chosen cars other than Teslas solely for
                that reason. A lot of Tesla owners and would-be owners wish Tesla supported CarPlay — and I would wager
                heavily that GM never delivers a system that’s as good as Tesla’s, let alone CarPlay.</p>

            <p>And the fact that GM is doing this in collaboration with Google already puts them in different territory
                than Tesla or Rivian, who’ve created their own entire software stacks. If GM is only going to support
                its own automotive software system, they ought to be willing <em>and able</em> to do the entire thing
                themselves, with confidence that they’ll provide a best-in-class experience for owners. Otherwise this
                seems like a data grab by Google — collecting location, search, and music/podcast listening data from
                every driver of every vehicle GM eventually sells with this system — and a SaaS revenue grab by GM. <a
                        href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/gm-plans-phase-out-apple-carplay-evs-with-googles-help-2023-03-31/">From
                    the Reuters report that broke this news</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Buyers of GM EVs with the new systems will get access to Google
                    Maps and Google Assistant, a voice command system, at no extra
                    cost for eight years, GM said. GM said the future infotainment
                    systems will offer applications such as Spotify’s music service,
                    Audible and other services that many drivers now access via
                    smartphones.</p>

                <p>“We do believe there are subscription revenue opportunities for
                    us,” Kummer said. GM Chief Executive Mary Barra is aiming for
                    $20 billion to $25 billion in annual revenue from subscriptions
                    by 2030.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>This sounds like a decision motivated entirely by a desire to generate a significant new services revenue
                stream, and not at all motivated by a desire to create the best possible driving/passenger
                experience.</p>

            <p>One influential group that knows the importance of CarPlay integration are car dealers. Say what you want
                about car salespeople, they know exactly what motivates buying decisions. I suspect GM corporate is
                getting an earful from GM dealers regarding this decision. I don’t know if GM is planning to share that
                future subscription revenue with dealers, but they won’t get a penny from every sale lost to a rival
                whose cars do support CarPlay.<sup id="fnr2-2023-04-10"><a href="#fn2-2023-04-10">2</a></sup></p>

            <p>20 years ago Apple presented the Mac as the ideal “digital hub” — the connection between all of one’s
                disparate devices, from MP3 players to cameras. A decade later, Apple went all-in on iCloud, and cloud
                computing in general, as the new hub. But in many ways our phones are our new digital hubs. They serve a
                very different role from what Macs and PCs did 20 years ago. Rather than serve as a hub for
                <em>hardware</em> peripherals, our phones serve as our primary hub for <em>software</em> services and
                apps. CarPlay exemplifies that role.</p>

            <div class="footnotes">
                <hr/>
                <ol>

                    <li id="fn1-2023-04-10">
                        <p>I wonder how much of a factor it is that Apple has spent the last decade not-so-secretly
                            working on creating its own line of cars? There’s no way GM would ever integrate a software
                            system from, say, Ford or Honda. But so why integrate CarPlay, which comes from a company
                            that seemingly wants to compete with existing automakers? Apple’s own car ambitions make
                            CarPlay integration, to some extent, seem like a wolf in sheep’s clothing.&nbsp;<a
                                    href="#fnr1-2023-04-10" class="footnoteBackLink"
                                    title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
                    </li>

                    <li id="fn2-2023-04-10">
                        <p>I wonder too about car rental fleets. I’d be furious today if I rented a car that didn’t
                            support CarPlay. I might be willing to learn a new system in a new car I bought, but when I
                            rent a car, I just want to connect my iPhone and get the navigation, music, and podcast
                            experience I already know.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2023-04-10" class="footnoteBackLink"
                                                               title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a>
                        </p>
                    </li>

                </ol>
            </div>


            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>★ GM, CarPlay, and iPhones</title></entry>
    <entry>
        <title>WorkOS</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=df2023"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqg"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/09/workos"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39832</id>
        <published>2023-04-09T19:17:25Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-09T19:17:25Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. WorkOS is like “Stripe for enterprise features.” They
                make it easy for developers to build features needed by enterprise customers, such as Single Sign-On and
                SCIM.</p>

            <p>Shipping these feature is important because they enable selling upmarket for bigger deals. Without these
                features, the IT department will reject your app. But these enterprise features are complex and
                time-consuming to build yourself, usually taking months.</p>

            <p>With WorkOS you can integrate and ship enterprise features in minutes. Beautiful API docs guide you
                through every step of the way, and transparent pricing scales based on usage. It’s a product built by
                developers, for developers.</p>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS’" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/09/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Kirk McElhearn: ‘Apple Music Classical (Mostly) Plays the Right Chords’</title>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://tidbits.com/2023/03/29/apple-music-classical-mostly-plays-the-right-chords/"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uqf"/>
        <link rel="related" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/08/mcelhearn-apple-music-classical"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023:/linked//6.39831</id>
        <published>2023-04-08T19:12:29Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-09T00:30:33Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Kirk McElhearn has a comprehensive review of the new Apple Music Classical app/catalog at TidBITS:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Due to the way classical works have been cataloged over time, many
                    of their names are unique, at least for the most famous composers.
                    Schubert’s compositions are <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schubert_Thematic_Catalogue">cataloged
                        according to the work of
                        Otto Erich Deutsch</a>, hence the D before work numbers. Bach’s
                    works have BWV numbers, for <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bach-Werke-Verzeichnis">Bach-Werke-Verzeichnis,
                        or Bach works
                        catalog</a>. For other composers, opus numbers are used,
                    referring to a specific publication. So for Beethoven, we have Op.
                    26: Piano Sonata No. 12 in A♭ major, which is a single piano
                    sonata, and Op. 27, which contains two piano sonatas, No. 1: Piano
                    Sonata No. 13 in E♭ major, and No. 2: Piano Sonata No. 14 in C♯
                    minor, also known as the Moonlight Sonata.</p>

                <p>The point of this somewhat lengthy preamble is to explain why
                    searching for classical music is so much more complicated than
                    searching for popular music. You may want to listen to a specific
                    work by a given composer, but also by one of your favorite
                    performers. And, as you can see with the example of the Schubert
                    sonata, work names are not always as simple as Bach’s Goldberg
                    Variations. Metadata is the key to managing classical music.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>I’ve seen some people wondering if Apple Music Classical is the first step toward per-genre apps: Apple
                Music Rock, Apple Music Rap, Apple Music Jazz, etc. That’s almost certainly not going to happen.
                Classical music is different, because it doesn’t fit in the simple categorization of artist → album →
                song. Classical music demands different and more metadata attached to the music, <em>and</em> a
                different interface for browsing, discovering, and managing that music.</p>

            <p>One seemingly weird thing about Apple Music Classical: it’s iPhone-only for now. McElhearn writes:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>It also seems like it should be trivial to add Apple Music
                    Classical to the Music app on the desktop. Adding a sidebar entry
                    would not change the interface much, and since all of the content
                    in the Apple Music Classical app is HTML, the Music app would have
                    no problem displaying it. It’s the exact same type of content that
                    Apple Music uses.</p>

                <p>All this makes the Apple Music Classical app seem like an
                    experiment. It’s quite polished for a 1.0 release, and, despite
                    the issues that I’ve mentioned above that will irritate classical
                    music fans, it’s a generally successful attempt to provide a
                    better way to access classical music. Apple should be praised for
                    paying so much attention to a genre that represents only 2–3% of
                    the overall music market.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <div>
                <a title="Permanent link to ‘Kirk McElhearn: ‘Apple Music Classical (Mostly) Plays the Right Chords’’"
                   href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/08/mcelhearn-apple-music-classical">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
            </div>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/a_bit_of_follow-up_on_wavelength"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/uqc"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023://1.39828</id>
        <published>2023-04-05T00:00:46Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-08T19:50:03Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <summary type="text">A few additional tidbits regarding Wavelength.</summary>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Lots of great feedback from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/03/wavelength">my post last week</a>
                about <a href="https://www.wavelength.app/">Wavelength</a>. A few that I’ve noted:</p>

            <ul>
                <li><p>Ben Thompson and I spent last Friday’s episode of <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Dithering</a>
                    talking about Wavelength. You should subscribe! We even started a Dithering group in
                    Wavelength — the link is in the show notes for the episode. (And speaking of Dithering, the show is
                    on vacation this week — a fact we neglected to mention on air. Sorry about that.)</p></li>
                <li><p>Semafor editor-in-chief Ben Smith devoted the “One Good Chat” feature <a
                        href="https://www.semafor.com/newsletter/03/29/2023/vinod-khosla-openais-first-vc-investor">in
                    this newsletter last week</a> to a group chat between him, Wavelength’s founders, and the Wavelength
                    AI bot. It’s brief, but it conveys a sense of how fun it is to engage AI chat in a group context.
                </p></li>
                <li><p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35334613#35335289">Hacker News had a pretty good
                    thread</a> about Wavelength (and my post about it). </p></li>
                <li><p><a href="https://twitter.com/wattmaller1/status/1641605786349580289">Matt Waller tweeted my very
                    favorite AI interaction</a> with Wavelength’s bot to date.</p></li>
            </ul>

            <p><strong>Everything else:</strong> Feedback from those of you who’ve started using Wavelength has been
                very consistent. The top missing features: reactions/tapbacks, editing messages to fix typos, and
                search. And the biggest issue is, perhaps, group discoverability: How do you find good groups to join? A
                side effect of Wavelength’s focus on privacy is that there’s no public directory of groups. I suspect
                this will sort itself out as Wavelength gains traction, but in the meantime, it can seem a bit quiet if
                you don’t know many other people using Wavelength.</p>

            <p><strong>One more thing:</strong> The fact that Wavelength has no Android app yet comes up repeatedly, for
                obvious reasons. Less obvious and very curious to me is this: I haven’t seen a single complaint about
                the fact that there is no Windows app, nor any announced plans to create one. I’m not sure why that is.
                The Mac app is very important to me — I really can’t imagine spending much time using any messaging
                platform that doesn’t have a Mac client, or at the very least a web app. But Windows users are OK with
                that?</p>

            <p><strong>Bonus postscript:</strong> <a href="https://nickpunt.com/blog/group-messagings-balancing-act/">Nick
                Punt wrote a thoughtful post</a> with suggestions for making the presentation of threads in Wavelength
                feel more organized without increasing friction.</p>


            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>★ A Bit of Follow-Up on Wavelength</title></entry>
    <entry>

        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html"
              href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/the_case_of_the_iphone_case_poll"/>
        <link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/uq9"/>
        <id>tag:daringfireball.net,2023://1.39825</id>
        <published>2023-04-04T00:56:14Z</published>
        <updated>2023-04-10T19:17:13Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>John Gruber</name>
            <uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
        </author>
        <summary type="text">A poll about iPhone case usage, and my own iPhone 14 case recommendations.</summary>
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
            <p>Last month <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/109956599103256092">I posted to Mastodon</a> to
                complain that I’d somehow cracked the back of my iPhone for the second year running. I say “somehow”
                because I hadn’t dropped my phone — I have no idea what caused the crack. My complaint:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Second year in a row that the back cracked on my iPhone. Can’t
                    wait until they figure out a way to stop making the backs out of
                    glass. What a terrible material for a phone frame in every regard
                    other than allowing for inductive charging.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>My complaint, I think, is undeniably valid: glass, all things considered, is a rather terrible material
                for the back of a phone. The biggest upside of glass is that it allows for inductive charging. It’s also
                good for allowing wireless antennas to pass through signals. Subjectively, you can argue that glass
                makes for a premium look and feel. But glass is undeniably fragile. An expensive product you carry
                around in your pocket or purse ought to be made of sturdy materials, not fragile ones. Plastic would
                work, but plastic isn’t a luxury material.</p>

            <p>Inevitably, many of the responses I got were along the lines of “<em>That’s what you get for not using a
                case.</em>” There’s a subset of people who consider phone cases mandatory, not optional. That’s not an
                altogether unreasonable stance, but to me it only proves the point that, if the inductive charging and
                wireless signal pass-through issues could be solved, phone backs ought to be made out of a much more
                durable material than glass. Apple has <a
                        href="https://www.cnet.com/pictures/scenes-from-the-iphone-4-antenna-press-event-photos/24/">never</a>
                designed iPhones thinking they <em>need</em> to be in a case.</p>

            <p>I’m not a materials engineer and I have no suggestions for a material to replace glass. I’m just saying
                that ideally, Apple would find a material that looks good, feels good, isn’t slippery, allows inductive
                charging and wireless signals to pass through, <em>and</em> is crack and scratch-resistant. Also:
                lightweight. At the moment, only <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unobtainium">unobtainium</a>
                seemingly fits the bill.</p>

            <p>The whole thing got me wondering how many of my followers use a case on their phones. So I asked in a
                poll, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/109967265407586630">on both Mastodon</a> <a
                        href="https://twitter.com/gruber/status/1632180244743323654">and Twitter</a>:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>How do you typically — meaning, majority of the time — carry
                    your iPhone?</p>

                <ul>
                    <li>No case</li>
                    <li>Apple case</li>
                    <li>Third-party case</li>
                </ul>
            </blockquote>

            <p>Let’s just get this out of the way: the people who follow me on Mastodon and Twitter are, of course, not
                representative of the general public. I mean come on, that should go without saying. (My question even
                presupposes that everyone answering owns an iPhone.) But that doesn’t mean that the case choices of
                people who follow me aren’t interesting.</p>

            <p>This poll intrigued me in two ways: (a) the answers to the poll, and (b) as a test of my relative
                engagement on Mastodon and Twitter. Both aspects surprised me. Here are the overall poll results,
                combining over 17,000 responses from Mastodon and Twitter:</p>

            <ul>
                <li>No case: 31%</li>
                <li>Apple case: 34%</li>
                <li>Third-party case: 36%</li>
            </ul>

            <p>I started the Twitter poll a few hours after the Mastodon poll, but ran them on the same day (March 4),
                for the same duration (24 hours), and with the exact same language. There were 9,171 responses on
                Mastodon (split 30/35/35 percent, respectively) and 7,880 responses on Twitter (split 31/32/37
                percent).</p>

            <p>So on the engagement front, Mastodon flat out won, by a margin of over 1,000 responses, despite the fact
                that I have only <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber">39,000 followers on Mastodon</a>, compared to
                <a href="https://twitter.com/gruber">362,500 followers on Twitter</a>. Again, by no means am I even
                vaguely trying to argue that Mastodon is a more popular platform with more engagement than Twitter <em>overall</em>.
                But amongst <em>my</em> followers, it clearly is. I expected Mastodon to fare well in this test, but I
                did not expect it to win.<sup id="fnr1-2023-04-03"><a href="#fn1-2023-04-03">1</a></sup></p>

            <p>As for the poll results, I was even more surprised, both by the number of “no case” responses (nearly a
                full third)<sup id="fnr2-2023-04-03"><a href="#fn2-2023-04-03">2</a></sup> and by the number of case
                users who buy Apple’s own.</p>

            <p>It seems hard to find any polling or surveys on case usage amongst the general population. Best I’ve
                found is <a
                        href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/368627/us-protective-case-usage-among-smartphone-owners/">this
                    poll of U.S. smartphone owners from 2017</a> that showed 79 percent use a case. Observationally I’d
                have guessed the answer would be more like 85–90 percent, but ~80 percent certainly feels plausible.</p>

            <h2>I Don’t Always Drink Beer, but When I Do, I Prefer Dos Equis</h2>

            <p>For most of the year, in most situations, I have always carried my iPhones sans case. But I do buy a few
                cases each year, and I do use them occasionally. Sometimes I use a case in the coldest months of winter,
                when I wear gloves outdoors and my ungloved hands are often cold — I seem more likely to drop, or almost
                drop, my iPhone in cold weather. Sometimes I use a case while travelling, when I use my phone as a
                camera more often than on typical days, for added grip. And sometimes I just get bored and put on a case
                for a few days just for the hell of it.</p>

            <p>I don’t care for Apple’s silicone cases because I don’t like the rubbery, mushy-feeling buttons. And I
                don’t care for the look or feel of Apple’s clear cases. Apple’s leather cases look and feel nice, and
                their metal buttons are, by far, the best-feeling buttons on any cases I’ve ever tried. But there’s one
                aspect shared by all of Apple’s cases that I dislike: the protective rim goes around the entire edge of
                the iPhone, including the bottom.</p>

            <p>I much prefer iPhone cases with no bottom lip — it makes the swipe-up-from-the-bottom gesture more
                pleasant, and that’s a gesture I make dozens of times per day every day. Apple’s cases <a
                        href="https://www.apple.com/sg_smb_5200/shop/product/MR6F2FE/A/iphone-x-silicone-case-spicy-orange">used
                    to have no bottom lip</a> — but a couple of years ago they changed. My guess is that <a
                        href="https://youtu.be/_UnXGBotjwo?t=146">too many people</a> feel like they “need” a case whose
                protective edge goes all the way around. With each passing year it seems harder to find any iPhone cases
                with no bottom lip.</p>

            <p>I own two cases for my iPhone 14 Pro that I’m happy to recommend, and a third worthy of an honorable
                mention. All have built-in MagSafe support, and none have a bottom lip:</p>

            <ul>
                <li><p><a
                        href="https://bullstrap.co/collections/magsafe-gear/products/magsafe-iphone-cases-sienna?variant=42427776762050">Bullstrap’s
                    $85 leather case</a>. I’ve bought cases from Bullstrap now for a few years running. They’re a lot
                    like Apple’s own leather cases, but with no bottom lip, and with a distinctive rounded bulge for the
                    camera cutout. I find Bullstrap’s rounded camera bulge much more pleasant-feeling than Apple’s sharp
                    plastic insert. I don’t understand why more cases don’t have a camera cutout like this. Bullstrap
                    also has a slightly bigger, and thus slightly nicer, cutout for the mute switch than Apple’s cases
                    do. Bullstrap’s leather is nice, and ages well. I have almost embarrassingly sweaty hands during hot
                    weather, so leather cases tend to darken, quickly, in my grip. <a
                            href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2023/04/bullstrap-case-before-after.jpeg">Here’s a
                        side-by-side shot</a> of my year-old Bullstrap iPhone 13 Pro case and my then-brand-new iPhone
                    14 Pro case, both in “Sienna” brown. My one and only knock against Bullstrap’s case is their plastic
                    buttons. They’re fine buttons, but they’re not as nice as Apple’s metal ones, and for $85 I don’t
                    think it’s unreasonable to expect excellent buttons.</p></li>
                <li><p><a href="https://www.ipitaka.com/products/magez-case-3-for-iphone-14?variant=40305657479238">Pitaka’s
                    $60 MagEZ Case 3 aramid fiber case</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aramid">Aramid
                    fiber</a> is both lightweight and strong — it’s used in body armor under the brand name Kevlar. I’ve
                    been buying Pitaka cases for a few years, too. These cases are lightweight and so thin that they
                    have cutouts for the side buttons and mute switch. This case is less about drop protection and more
                    about grip. The feel of aramid fiber is a bit hard to describe — it’s soft, and feels a bit like
                    leather. It doesn’t feel rubbery or plasticky at all. It’s not grippy per se, but it’s not at all
                    slippery. If I could make one request of Pitaka, it would be for a case that is all black, instead
                    of striped black-and-gray.</p></li>
                <li><p>Honorable mention: <a href="https://ansoncalder.com/products/iphone-14-cases-with-magsafe">Anson
                    Calder’s $80 leather case</a>. This case is sort of a cross between Bullstrap’s and Pitaka’s — it’s
                    leather, like Bullstrap’s, but has cutouts for the buttons on both sides, like Pitaka’s. Those
                    cutouts eliminate any complaints about buttons on the case itself, but because leather cases are
                    thicker than Pitaka’s super-thin aramid cases, it’s a bit harder to press the buttons on the phone
                    itself than with Pitaka’s. Bonus points to Anson Calder for having no logo or indicia on the outside
                    of the case at all.</p></li>
                <li><p>Special mention: <a
                        href="https://ryanlondon.com/collections/iphone-14-series-leather-case/products/leather-iphone-14-pro-shell-case-magsafe-black">Ryan
                    London’s $56 leather case</a>. I neither own nor have seen one of these in person, but <a
                        href="https://atp.fm/510">as discussed on Accidental Tech Podcast back in November</a>, my
                    fellow nitpicker extraordinaire John Siracusa bought both the Bullstrap and Ryan London cases, and
                    deems them indistinguishable, aside from their embossed logos. (Perhaps they’re both based on some
                    sort of white-label design from a manufacturer in China?) Bullstrap embosses their logo centered on
                    the back of the case, like Apple does. Ryan London’s branding is more subtle (and in fact isn’t
                    pictured in their own product photography): a subtle “R” embossed on the edge with the volume
                    buttons.</p></li>
            </ul>

            <div class="footnotes">
                <hr/>
                <ol>

                    <li id="fn1-2023-04-03">
                        <p>I will also note that I didn’t mention that I was running the same poll on both platforms. I
                            know none of these polls are rigorous, but I was thinking that if I mentioned up front that
                            I was running it on both, Mastodon users might have been encouraged to respond to show their
                            support for the fledgling platform. I just wanted to see how many people responded to the
                            poll simply because they wanted to answer the question.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2023-04-03"
                                                                                            class="footnoteBackLink"
                                                                                            title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a>
                        </p>
                    </li>


                    <li id="fn2-2023-04-03">
                        <p>My friend Cabel Sasser, back in September: “AppleCare+ is my go-to iPhone case.” If you read
                            the replies to my poll, you’ll see <a href="https://www.apple.com/support/products/iphone/">AppleCare+</a>
                            mentioned several times amongst the no-casers. AppleCare+ is expensive (two years of
                            coverage: $150 for an iPhone SE; $220–270 for iPhones 12-14, depending on the model) but
                            with it, screen or back glass repairs cost just $29 per incident. Me personally, though, I’m
                            a gambler: I haven’t purchased AppleCare for any product since my Macintosh LC for college
                            in 1991, and through some combination of good fortune and careful handling, I’m now way
                            ahead for having forgone it so many times. If I could get the cracked back glass on my
                            iPhone 14 Pro repaired for just a $29 deductible, I suppose I’d do it, but as it stands I’ll
                            tell myself the crack adds character.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2023-04-03"
                                                                          class="footnoteBackLink"
                                                                          title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a>
                        </p>
                    </li>

                </ol>
            </div>


            ]]>
        </content>
        <title>★ The Case of the iPhone Case Poll</title></entry>
</feed><!-- THE END -->
